<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "file:////voyager/templates/DTDs/LNUK/KnowHow/KnowHow.dtd"><?Pub EntList mdash reg #8364 #176 #169 #8230 #10003 #x2610 #x2611 #x2612 #x2613?><?Pub Inc?><kh:document xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core" xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn" xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/header" xmlns:kh="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/kh" xmlns:lnb="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/lnb" xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci" xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr" xmlns:atict="http://www.arbortext.com/namespace/atict"><atict:info tracking="on" ref="2" print="" color="" /><atict:user user="navarrfx" fullname="Navarro, Francis (LNG-CON)" color="#40A800" /><atict:user user="Corrigs" fullname="Corrigan, Suzanna (LNG-LON)" /><atict:user user="jimened2" fullname="Jimenez, Dahn Steven (REPH-ILO)" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="STATERJM" fullname="Sta. Teresa, Jana M. (REPH-MNL )" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="PRESBIAT" fullname="Presbitero, Alexandria Jhul T. (REPH-MNL )" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="excondpa" fullname="Exconde, Paul Jerdan A. (LNG-CON)" color="#B00050" /><atict:user user="DORIAAX" fullname="Doria, Abegail G. (REPH-MNL )" color="#FF2000" /><atict:user user="DELAROPE" fullname="Dela Rosa, Patricia Therese E. (REPH-MNL )" color="#008050" /><atict:user user="hernanat" fullname="Hernandez, Ara Beatriz T. (REPH-MNL)" color="#C000C0" /><atict:user user="MALABAGC" fullname="Malabad, Gil C. (REPH-MNL)" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="MAMPUSTIZ" fullname="Mampusti, Zsereena Rose (REPH-MNL)" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="yeoe" fullname="Yeo, Elsa Hui Seen (LNG-LON)" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="nixeysx" fullname="Nixey, Stephen A. (LNG-LON)" color="#00A0A0" /><atict:user user="Smitha7" fullname="Smith, Anthony J. (LNG-LON)" color="#909000" /><atict:user user="millinex" fullname="Millington, Emma (LNG-LON)" color="#8000FF" /><atict:user user="jahodovs" fullname="" color="yellow" /><atict:user user="MILLINEX" fullname="Millington, Emma (LNG-LON)" color="#0050D0" /><atict:user user="Levenejx" fullname="Levene, Jonathan (LNG-LON)" color="#D06000" /><kh:body><kh:document-title>Types of derivatives</kh:document-title><kh:mini-summary>This Practice Note provides an overview of swaps (including interest rate, currency, commodity and credit default swaps), forward rate agreements, futures and options).</kh:mini-summary><core:para>The main types of derivatives are:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>swaps</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>forwards</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>futures, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>options</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>This Practice Note explains the key features of each of the above types of derivatives.</core:para><core:para>For a general introduction to derivatives, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:13795E25-49A7-4868-81FE-D70BCFDC140D"><lnci:content>Introductory guide to derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_116583">Swaps</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.2]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.2]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>A swap describes a wide variety of derivative transactions. Since their inception in the 1980s, swaps have evolved into a worldwide market encompassing trillions of pounds worldwide in notional value. They are subject to different regulations and laws depending on the market in which they are traded. Swaps are generally documented under the International Swaps and Derivatives Association (ISDA) framework. For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:C9DA7671-21A2-4B40-A2E5-ACFA748E4AF5"><lnci:content>Derivatives—ISDA documentation framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite>).</core:para><core:para>For more information on why parties enter into swaps, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_116579" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:7100E8F7-CFCC-42D7-8564-C6A53F419A52"><lnci:content>The nature of financial derivatives—Key uses of derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>In a swap, two parties enter into a contract in which they agree to exchange payment streams. Each party to the swap makes regular payments to the other. The payments made under the swap by one party are calculated on a different basis to the payments made by the other party.</core:para><core:para>At the beginning of the life of a swap, its net value should, in theory, be zero. During the life of the swap, rates will move and the swap will become an asset to one party and a liability to the other. Once a swap becomes an asset to one party, that party is exposed to the credit risk of the other party.</core:para><core:para>The majority of swaps are traded over-the-counter (OTC). OTC derivatives are negotiated and traded privately between two parties (one of which is usually a financial institution) and tailored to the needs of the particular parties. They are not traded on exchanges. OTC contracts constitute by far the largest part of the derivatives market.</core:para><core:para>The key types of swaps are:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>interest rate swaps</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>currency (rate) swaps</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>commodity swaps, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>credit default swaps</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><tr:secsub1><core:title>Interest rate swaps</core:title><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Interest rate swap diagram.png" /></core:figure><!--Editor: insert new graphic - interest rate swap diagram. The graphic should be published in PNG format, and that the white padding to the right side of the image should be kept.--><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.4]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Interest rate swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.4]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>The most common type of interest rate swap (known as a fixed-for-floating interest rate swap) involves:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>one party making payments by reference to a variable (or floating) rate of interest, eg <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_368018" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:85BD2B28-1234-4735-965F-129118BA1ECB"><lnci:content>SONIA</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Editor: check the link to glossary is working-->, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the other party making payments based on a fixed rate of interest</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>In a typical loan transaction, borrowers may enter into interest rate swaps with each other to hedge against the risk of an increase in the interest payments it is making to the lender. For example:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>party A is under an obligation to pay interest at a floating rate of SONIA plus 3% on a loan of £10m to bank A</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party B is under an obligation to pay interest at a fixed rate of 5% on a loan of €10m to bank B</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A does not want to take the risk of SONIA increasing and would prefer to pay a fixed rate</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party B is prepared to take the risk of SONIA increasing</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>in effect, party A and party B swap interest rate obligations:</core:para><core:sub1list type="bullet"><core:sub1listitem><core:para>party A pays regular amounts to party B equal to interest at a fixed rate of 5% on a loan of €10m—party B uses that amount to pay bank B</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>party B pays regular amounts to party A equal to interest at a floating rate of SONIA plus 3% on a loan of €10m—party A uses that amount to pay bank A</core:para></core:sub1listitem></core:sub1list></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Currency rate swaps</core:title><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Currency swap transaction diagram - 1 Initial exchange.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Currency swap transaction diagram - 2 Periodic payments.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Currency swap transaction diagram - 3 Final Exchange.png" /></core:figure><!--Editor: insert new graphic - currency swap transaction diagrams in the following order - 1 initial exchange, 2 periodic payments and 3 final exchange--><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Currency swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Currency products: Henderson on Derivatives [3.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>A typical currency swap transaction involves two parties exchanging amounts in different currencies, the relative amounts being calculated on the basis of an agreed exchange rate. Currency rate swaps are typically used by a party who has an obligation to a third party in one currency but receives its income in a different currency. By entering into a currency rate swap, that party can hedge against the risk of adverse changes in exchange rates, for example:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>party A receives the majority of its income in euros</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A has entered into a Sterling loan with its bank and is obliged to repay the loan in Sterling</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A does not want to take the risk of an unfavourable movement in the Sterling/euro exchange rate which would result in it not having enough income to repay its loan to the bank</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party B is prepared to take the risk of movements in the Sterling/euro exchange rate</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A and party B agree to a fixed Sterling/euro exchange rate at the start of the term of party X's loan with its bank:</core:para><core:sub1list type="bullet"><core:sub1listitem><core:para>party B pays regular amounts to party A in Sterling at the pre-agreed Sterling/euro exchange rate (calculated by reference to the repayment schedule under party X's loan with its bank)—party A uses that amount to repay its Sterling loan</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>party A uses its euro income to pay equivalent regular amounts to party Y in euros at the pre-agreed Sterling/euro exchange rate</core:para></core:sub1listitem></core:sub1list></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>It is a slightly more complicated transaction than an interest rate swap as it typically involves three stages:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>an initial exchange of amounts in different currencies</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>periodic payments during the life of the transaction in the currency each party received on the initial exchange, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>a final exchange by the parties of the currency amounts reversing the currency exchanged at initial exchange</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>Currency swaps can also involve interest rate swaps, in which case they are known as cross-currency interest rate swaps. In these swaps, the rate of interest may be a fixed rate for one party and floating rate for the other party. If this is the case, diagram 2 reflecting the periodic payments made during the life of the swap will be amended so that it mirrors an interest rate swap.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Commodity swaps</core:title><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Commodity swaps - Payment flows when commodity is above agreed rate.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Commodity swaps - Payment flows when commodity is below agreed rate of 10.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Commodity swaps - Payment flows when commodity is at agreed rate of 10.png" /></core:figure><!--Editor: insert new graphic commodity swap transaction diagrams in the following order - 1 Payment flows when commodity is above agreed rate, 2 Payment flows when commodity is below agreed rate of 10 and 3 Payment flows when commodity is at agreed rate of 10--><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.10]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Commodity (and other) derivatives: Henderson on Derivatives [3.10]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.11]" type="comm"><lnci:content>2005 ISDA Commodity (and other) definitions: Henderson on Derivatives [3.11]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.12]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Commodity transactions: Henderson on Derivatives [3.12]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>A typical commodity swap involves an agreement between two parties to fix the price of a commodity and to make regular payments to each other based on the difference between the fixed price agreed between the parties and the market price of the commodity. Commodity swaps are used where one party is exposed to fluctuations in commodity prices, either because it has agreed to buy a commodity in the future at the market price and does not want the price to increase or because it is relying on the income from selling the commodity and does not want the price to decrease. By entering into a commodity swap, the risk of an adverse change in commodity prices can be hedged against. For example:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>party A wishes to buy a certain amount of corn per month for the next year</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A is concerned that the price of corn will increase over the next year</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party B is prepared to take the risk that the price of corn will increase over the next year</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A and party B agree to a notional fixed price for corn at the start of the year, say, for example £10 per bag of corn (the swap price)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party A purchases corn in the market place throughout the year:</core:para><core:sub1list type="bullet"><core:sub1listitem><core:para>if party A purchases corn in the market place for more than £10 per bag, party B pays the difference between the swap price and the market price to party A</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>if party A purchases corn in the market place for less than £10 per bag, party A pays the difference between the swap price and the market price to party B</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>if party A purchases corn in the marketplace for exactly £10 per bag, no payment is made by either party</core:para></core:sub1listitem></core:sub1list></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the net effect is that party A always pays £10 per bag for the corn and that party B takes the risk in the fluctuating market price of the corn</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For more information about commodity swaps, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:5823ECB8-613E-430A-B0D4-EEFB16DEF701"><lnci:content>Commodity derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Credit default swaps</core:title><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Credit default swap structure diagram - Cash settled.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Credit default swap structure diagram - Physically delivered.png" /></core:figure><core:figure><kh:graphic filename="Credit default swap structure diagram - Auction settlement.png" /></core:figure><!--Editor: insert new graphics for credit default swaps diagrams cash, physical and auction settlement)--><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [5.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Credit default swap: Henderson on Derivatives [5.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>The most common type of credit derivative transaction is a credit default swap (CDS). This is a transaction between two parties which is based on the creditworthiness of a third party, known as the reference entity. The protection buyer is the party that is purchasing the credit protection and the protection seller is the party that is selling that credit protection. A CDS contract is traded OTC and is typically an individually negotiated unfunded contract. The protection buyer will pay a premium to the protection seller, usually by way of periodic payments, in exchange for the protection seller agreeing to bear the credit risk of the underlying reference entity. If a credit event occurs on the underlying reference entity, the protection seller must compensate the protection buyer for its loss by means of a defined settlement procedure. This may be on the basis of auction, cash or physical settlement depending on the terms of the CDS contract.</core:para><core:para>In a typical CDS contract:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the protection seller (party A) and protection buyer (party B) enter into a CDS contract</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>party B agrees to pay a fee or 'premium' to party A periodically throughout the life of the CDS—this fee is based on the notional value of the CDS, and this is the amount of exposure that party A has agreed to assume</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>in exchange, party A agrees to make a payment to party B if a credit event occurs on the underlying reference entity</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>if a credit event does occur, the CDS contract will settle on the basis of auction, cash or physical settlement, depending on what is agreed in the contract and once the CDS contract has settled, the CDS contract will terminate (for more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:6B26F94E-B3D8-4534-AC88-73263500DE9D"><lnci:content>Credit derivatives—settlement procedures</lnci:content></lnci:cite>) </core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For more information on credit default swaps, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:B56EDE4E-6879-4015-ADD1-AA79C7B58A68"><lnci:content>Credit default swap (CDS) transactions</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Other types of swap</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.6]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Caps floors and collars: Henderson on Derivatives [2.6]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>There are a number of other different types of swap that can be entered into including:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>total return swaps (see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F2F38126-1A27-4544-9CB3-A5887C3AEE04"><lnci:content>Total return swaps</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:FF2CB8D1-4B9D-4C48-A9B7-32EE313494B0"><lnci:content>Total return swap (TRS) structure diagram</lnci:content></lnci:cite> for more information on total return swaps)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.7]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Swaptions and options to terminate: Henderson on Derivatives [2.7]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>swaptions (options on a swap)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>zero coupon swaps (for more information on how a zero coupon inflation swap works, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:B1F1A722-A5A8-49AB-A90F-EB91610C59EF"><lnci:content>Zero coupon inflation swap structure diagram</lnci:content></lnci:cite>), and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [7.14]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Forwards and additional leverage: Henderson on Derivatives [7.14]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>forward rate swaps</core:para></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_116584">Forwards</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [7.14]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Forwards and additional leverage: Henderson on Derivatives [7.14]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>Like swaps, forwards (or forward rate agreements) are an agreement to exchange payment streams. They are a type of OTC derivative.</core:para><core:para>They are an arrangement between two parties which allows them to hedge against interest rate risk:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>one party hedges against the risk of interest rates going down, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the other party hedges against the risk of interest rates going up</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>The parties agree to make a payment to the other at an agreed future settlement date based on the difference between the interest on a notional principal amount at a fixed rate of interest compared to interest on the same notional amount at a floating rate of interest. One party agrees to pay the fixed rate. The other party agrees to pay the floating rate.</core:para><core:para>On the settlement date:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>if the fixed rate is higher than the floating rate, the party that agreed to pay the fixed rate pays a sum calculated on the basis of the difference between the fixed and floating rates to the other party</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>if the floating rate is higher than the fixed rate, the party that agreed to pay the floating rate pays a sum calculated on the basis of the difference between the fixed and floating rates to the other party</core:para></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_116585">Futures</core:title><core:para>A future is a contract between two parties where one party agrees to buy and the other party agrees to sell an asset at a specific time in the future at a specific price. For example, futures are entered into in connection with the future price of a particular currency or commodity.</core:para><core:para>A futures contract is different from a commercial contract for sale where payment is made up front for the future delivery of goods. In a futures contract, the parties close out the transaction and settle up payments before the delivery date.</core:para><core:para>The terms of futures are standardised and as a result futures are only ever traded on exchanges. This is a key difference between a forward and a future as forwards are individually negotiated between the parties rather than being standardised. There is an active secondary market for futures because they are so standardised, whereas in contrast there is no secondary market for forwards.</core:para></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_116586">Options</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [4.4]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Options: Henderson on Derivatives [4.4]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>An option is a contract between two parties where one party agrees to buy and the other party agrees to sell an asset at a specific time in the future at a specific price. One party to the contract has the right to buy or sell the asset but is not obliged to do so. The party with the option pays a premium (ie a cash lump sum) to the other party.</core:para><core:para>A call option is where the party with the option to perform the contract is the buyer. A put option is where the party with the option to perform is the seller.</core:para><core:para>Options are traded on exchanges as well as OTC.</core:para></tr:secmain></kh:body><kh:related-content type="further-reading"><kh:references ref-type="further-reading"><!--Hi editor, I've inserted the normcite for the following journal as it is not pattern matching live. Please could you check that it is working once published?--><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The role of sustainability-linked derivatives in meeting global ESG goals (2021) 9 JIBFL 628</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>ESG derivatives: a look at recent Developments (2021) 7 JIBFL 482</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The UK's announcement of plans for synthetic LIBOR: panacea or pandora's box? (2020) 8 JIBFL 517</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>FCA regulation of interest rate hedging products: one rule for some? (2015) 7 JIBFL 425</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Termination provisions of swap agreements II (2015) 2 JIBFL 83</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para></kh:references></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="related-documents"><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:13795E25-49A7-4868-81FE-D70BCFDC140D"><lnci:content>Introductory guide to derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:ABD99018-F7B9-4DB3-8B61-CBA97E902F14"><lnci:content>Derivatives—key considerations—overview</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:7100E8F7-CFCC-42D7-8564-C6A53F419A52"><lnci:content>The nature of financial derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:2828B976-3364-4638-8006-FBABB540A6DE"><lnci:content>Derivatives—capacity and authority</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:C9DA7671-21A2-4B40-A2E5-ACFA748E4AF5"><lnci:content>Derivatives—ISDA documentation framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:6B26F94E-B3D8-4534-AC88-73263500DE9D"><lnci:content>Credit derivatives—settlement procedures</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:4D10980B-4DBD-4D5C-BEFE-3320CB4D0DA5"><lnci:content>Triggering and settling credit derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:5823ECB8-613E-430A-B0D4-EEFB16DEF701"><lnci:content>Commodity derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:B56EDE4E-6879-4015-ADD1-AA79C7B58A68"><lnci:content>Credit default swap (CDS) transactions</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:6B26F94E-B3D8-4534-AC88-73263500DE9D"><lnci:content>Credit derivatives—settlement procedures</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:FFEA7A52-3720-4065-B6ED-E1593D6F8E41"><lnci:content>Credit default swap (CDS) structure diagram—cash settlement</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:09D9B3D3-222F-43AE-901F-3CD4836247D8"><lnci:content>Credit default swap (CDS) structure diagram—physical settlement</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:48B53976-F65E-4EC0-A475-2414DF773625"><lnci:content>Credit default swap (CDS) structure diagram—auction settlement</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:0C8045CD-BF3D-45A6-A09A-E1F1B2BD355B"><lnci:content>Currency rate swap (CRS) structure diagram</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:90598570-79BD-4B8C-A866-C1B68309B8E0"><lnci:content>Credit derivatives—credit events</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F2F38126-1A27-4544-9CB3-A5887C3AEE04"><lnci:content>Total return swaps</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:FF2CB8D1-4B9D-4C48-A9B7-32EE313494B0"><lnci:content>Total return swap (TRS) structure diagram</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:B1F1A722-A5A8-49AB-A90F-EB91610C59EF"><lnci:content>Zero coupon inflation swap structure diagram</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="further-reading"><kh:references ref-type="further-reading"><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="LPICM, 1.202" type="comm"><lnci:content>Types of derivatives: Fuller: The Law &amp; Practice of International Capital Markets [1.201]–[1.217]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.1]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Basic structures, products and application: Henderson on Derivatives [2.1]–[2.7]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, 16.3" type="comm"><lnci:content>Evolution of derivatives documentation: Henderson on Derivatives [16.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.2]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.2]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.4]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Interest rate swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.4]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Currency swaps: Henderson on Derivatives [2.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Currency products: Henderson on Derivatives [3.3]–[3.7]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.10]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Commodity (and other) derivatives: Henderson on Derivatives [3.10]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.11]" type="comm"><lnci:content>2005 ISDA Commodity (and other) definitions: Henderson on Derivatives [3.11]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [3.12]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Commodity transactions: Henderson on Derivatives [3.12]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [5.3]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Credit default swap: Henderson on Derivatives [5.3]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.6]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Caps floors and collars: Henderson on Derivatives [2.6]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [2.7]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Swaptions and options to terminate: Henderson on Derivatives [2.7]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [7.14]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Forwards and additional leverage: Henderson on Derivatives [7.14]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, [4.4]" type="comm"><lnci:content>Options: Henderson on Derivatives [4.4]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="COLMPODT, 7.35" type="comm"><lnci:content>Interest Rate Swaps: Close-outs: The Law and Market Practice of OTC Derivative Terminations [7.35]–[7.36]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para></kh:references></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="external-links"><core:url address="www.isda.org/a/xWYgE/The-Value-of-OTC-Derivatives.pdf" type="https">ISDA report: The Value of OTC Derivatives: Empowering Organizations to Manage Risks, Enhance Returns and Optimize Liquidity</core:url></kh:related-content></kh:document>