<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "file:////voyager/templates/DTDs/LNUK/KnowHow/KnowHow.dtd"><kh:document xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core" xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn" xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/header" xmlns:kh="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/kh" xmlns:lnb="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/lnb" xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci" xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr" xmlns:atict="http://www.arbortext.com/namespace/atict"><kh:body><kh:document-title>Governing law, jurisdiction and arbitration clauses in finance documents</kh:document-title><!--AI: 22.10.25 NC using ChatGPT Enterprise, UK--><kh:mini-summary>This Practice Note explains what is meant by governing law and jurisdiction before discussing governing law and jurisdiction in more detail, including information on applicable rules. It looks at governing law clauses and jurisdiction clauses in finance transactions and considerations when deciding on whether to include exclusive, non-exclusive or asymmetric jurisdiction clauses. It also discusses service of process and process agents and contains a section on arbitration and arbitration clauses as an alternative to court proceedings.</kh:mini-summary><core:para>This Practice Note discusses governing law and jurisdiction in the context of finance transactions. It explains:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>what is meant by governing law and jurisdiction</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>governing law in more detail, including how the relevant governing law will be determined</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>jurisdiction in more detail, including applicable rules for determining jurisdiction</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>governing law clauses in finance transactions and when English law might not be appropriate</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>jurisdiction clauses in finance transactions, and considerations when deciding on whether to include an exclusive, non-exclusive or asymmetric jurisdiction clause</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>service of process and process agents, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>arbitration clauses</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>Information on governing law and jurisdiction can be found in the following Practice Notes:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:21E81B9B-D45D-4A87-A09F-12AEF25CC782"><lnci:content>Applicable law—a guide for dispute resolution practitioners</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3EE6523A-AE84-46C7-AAE7-E4288ED0E88B"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction—a guide for dispute resolution practitioners</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para></core:listitem></core:list><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087304">What is meant by governing law and jurisdiction?</core:title><core:para>Governing law and jurisdiction are two fundamentally different concepts.</core:para><tr:secsub1><core:title>Governing law</core:title><core:para>The governing law (sometimes referred to as the applicable law) is the law applied by the courts to determine a dispute between parties. Where the law is stipulated within a contract between the parties, this is known as the governing law clause.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Jurisdiction</core:title><core:para>Jurisdiction refers to the country whose courts are to apply the governing law. A jurisdiction clause is included in finance documents to allow the parties to specify the courts that are to have jurisdiction to hear disputes that arise in relation to the finance documents and to apply the governing law of the finance documents.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Do the countries specified in a governing law clause and a jurisdiction clause always have to be the same?</core:title><core:para>Jurisdiction clauses will typically designate the courts in the country by whose law the contract is governed, though this does not have to be and will not always be the case.</core:para><core:para>Even if the courts in the country of the governing law are designated, in a finance context, loan agreements will frequently include a non-exclusive (or asymmetric) jurisdiction clause. This enables the lenders to choose another jurisdiction in which to bring proceedings, if appropriate. See: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E4F83CAD-CF3B-4ACC-9077-C0231D741060" citeref="CITEID_1087309"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction clauses in finance transactions</lnci:content></lnci:cite> below.</core:para><core:para>Where a contract does not specify a governing law and/or jurisdiction, the applicable governing law and jurisdiction may not necessarily be the same.</core:para><core:para>An interesting example of this position occurred in the unreported decision of <core:emph typestyle="it">Berrocal v Warner Chappell Music Limited</core:emph> (3 October 2017) where the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court held that a clause requiring licences ‘shall be construed and shall always be subject to enforcement’ under the laws of New York was simply a governing law clause and did not amount to an exclusive jurisdiction clause in favour of the New York courts. It was held that the English courts had jurisdiction to hear the case albeit that it had to apply New York law to properly construe the contract including this provision. Had the parties wanted the New York courts to have jurisdiction, the licences should have included a jurisdiction clause to that effect.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Why are governing law and jurisdiction issues important in finance transactions?</core:title><core:para>Banking and finance lawyers will need to be aware of the main issues surrounding governing law and jurisdiction clauses because they become relevant in any dispute or enforcement proceedings.</core:para><core:para>While governing law and jurisdiction issues are typically straightforward on purely domestic transactions, the rules can be complex where there is a cross-border element which there often will be on finance transactions.</core:para><core:para>Where there is a cross-border element to a claim, there are three key questions for parties and their lawyers:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>which country’s laws will be applied by the court when hearing the substantive dispute? (the applicable law question)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>in which country should the claim be commenced? (the jurisdiction question)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>where can any judgment obtained be enforced? (the enforcement question)</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>These questions raise issues which are interrelated and should be considered together.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087305">What rules determine the applicable law/governing law of a contract?</core:title><core:para>Generally, parties have the freedom to choose the governing law of a contract. However, where they have failed to do so or have chosen a law which is prohibited for some reason, then the governing law will be determined by the application of the relevant legislation, convention, common law rules (in English courts) or civil law rules (where relevant) depending on, for example, the date of the contract.</core:para><core:para>In such circumstances, for domestic disputes, the governing law will be that of England and Wales. When dealing with international disputes, a number of laws may be of relevance to the parties, for example, the law of the different countries in which each party is situated or the law of the country in which performance of the contract is required. When applied, the laws of the different countries could lead to fundamentally different outcomes when determining a dispute between the parties. Agreeing and setting out the governing law of a contract is therefore extremely important. See Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:21E81B9B-D45D-4A87-A09F-12AEF25CC782"><lnci:content>Applicable law—a guide for dispute resolution practitioners</lnci:content></lnci:cite> for more information.</core:para><core:para>Finance documents will typically feature a ’governing law’ or ‘choice of law’ clause stating that the parties agree, in the event of a dispute arising out of the contract, that the law of a particular country will apply. The laws of any country may be chosen, even one that may have no apparent connection with the underlying contract at all. As an example, it may be the case that neither party wants to accept the other’s national law and so the parties agree to accept a neutral third-state law. English law has often been chosen in international finance contracts in such cases. For guidance, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:9CE73CBD-631B-4312-837E-18BDBD7130D6"><lnci:content>Applicable law clauses</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><tr:secsub1><core:title>An exception—the lex situs rule</core:title><core:para>One of the exceptions to the general rule of English law that parties are free to choose whichever laws they wish to govern contracts is that the validity of a transfer of a tangible asset is governed by the law of the country where the asset is situated at the time of the transfer (the lex situs) (<core:emph typestyle="it">Cammell v Sewell</core:emph> (1860) 5 H &amp; N 728 (not reported by LexisNexis®)). The general rule is that whether the creation or transfer of any proprietary interest in any movable (including the creation of security) is valid as a matter of English law, depends on whether the creation or transfer was valid under the law of the country in which the moveable was situated at the time of the transaction in question.</core:para><core:para>This rule will become particularly relevant, for example, when taking security over a tangible asset such as an aircraft. For insight, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:9186CE4F-E31F-41FD-802F-ED9A9231DB40" citeref="CITEID_136020"><lnci:content>Taking security over aircraft in aviation finance transactions—Creating an aircraft mortgage under English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087306">Choosing a governing law in finance transactions</core:title><tr:secsub1><core:title>Choosing the governing law</core:title><core:para>As a general rule, governing law clauses should be consistent across all finance documents relating to the same transaction.</core:para><core:para>However, it may be advisable for security documents relating to overseas assets to have a different governing law to the other finance documents. For example:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>security over land in an overseas jurisdiction is usually governed by the same law of the jurisdiction where the land is located, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>security over the shares of an overseas company is usually governed by the same law as the jurisdiction of incorporation of the company whose shares are being charged</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>Also, security granted over the rights under a contract is usually governed by the same law as the governing law of that contract.</core:para><core:para>For information on applicable law, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:21E81B9B-D45D-4A87-A09F-12AEF25CC782"><lnci:content>Applicable law—a guide for dispute resolution practitioners</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087309">Jurisdiction clauses in finance transactions</core:title><core:para>A key consideration when identifying which court has jurisdiction is to determine whether the parties have entered into a jurisdiction clause. These are typically entered into as part of the underlying contract between the parties but may also be entered into after a dispute has arisen. A jurisdiction agreement may be incorporated into a contract, for example by reference to standard terms and conditions or to another contract. It is therefore important to consider whether there is an agreement by incorporation. See Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:918B13F4-18FE-4B6B-B00B-3569AC6CB2A6"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements by incorporation—principles</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>Finance documents will typically include a jurisdiction clause. Note that some finance documents or side letters may incorporate the jurisdiction clause from the facility agreement by reference.</core:para><core:para>A jurisdiction clause may be drafted as an exclusive jurisdiction clause, non-exclusive jurisdiction clause or asymmetrical jurisdiction clause. Each has a different effect. For detailed guidance on understanding the different types, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:514F7713-2714-4580-BD0B-2ADCBE2286C2"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—introduction</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>Finance documents have traditionally included asymmetrical jurisdiction clauses—see <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E4F83CAD-CF3B-4ACC-9077-C0231D741060" citeref="CITEID_1087310"><lnci:content>What are the considerations when determining whether an exclusive, asymmetric or non-exclusive jurisdiction clause is most suitable?</lnci:content></lnci:cite> below and for more for detailed information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3987F0A7-EC9A-4C7A-A574-C13C09FE2651"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—asymmetric jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>The effect of a jurisdiction clause will depend on the particular regime the court is applying to determine jurisdiction, for example an international convention or the common law. Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:2FA26489-AC42-42A4-A63D-A9574124AF3D"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction rules</lnci:content></lnci:cite> sets out which jurisdiction rules the English courts will apply when determining which court has jurisdiction to determine a dispute.</core:para><core:para>Other jurisdictions will similarly have their own rules for determining the applicable jurisdiction rules—these will depend on the laws of the particular country as well as international conventions and agreements they have signed up to. For the EU this will also include EU regulations.</core:para><core:para>A defendant may agree to the court’s jurisdiction by submitting to its jurisdiction. For guidance, see: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editchecklist:9A1629B3-5A14-479D-B662-D567340B6AD0"><lnci:content>Determining whether a party has submitted to the court's jurisdiction—checklist</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><tr:secsub1><core:title>Competing jurisdiction clauses</core:title><core:para>It is sometimes the case that different finance documents may have different jurisdiction clauses even though they are part of the same financing transaction.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Loans and swaps</core:emph></core:para><core:para>A particularly common example is having a loan or intercreditor agreement with a jurisdiction clause in favour of the courts of one country and a swap agreement with a jurisdiction clause in favour of a second jurisdiction usually England or New York.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>BNP Paribas SA v Trattamento Rifiuti Metropolitani SPA [2019] EWCA Civ 768</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>In such cases, case law suggests that English courts will generally regard the jurisdiction clause in the swap agreement as determinative of the forum in which any dispute relating to the swap should be heard. If the swap is not part of the dispute, the jurisdiction clause in the other agreement will prevail. For example, see the Court of Appeal decision in <core:emph typestyle="it">BNP Paribas SA v Trattamento Rifiuti Metropolitani SPA</core:emph> in which the finance agreement provided for the Turin courts to have jurisdiction while the related swap transaction was on the terms of the ISDA Master Agreement ie English jurisdiction clause.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Overseas assets</core:emph></core:para><core:para>Security documents which relate to overseas assets will also typically have a jurisdiction clause in favour of the jurisdiction in which the relevant asset is located to assist enforcement.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087310">What are the considerations when determining whether an exclusive, asymmetric or non-exclusive jurisdiction clause is most suitable?</core:title><tr:secsub1><core:title>Exclusive jurisdiction clause</core:title><core:para>An exclusive jurisdiction clause will state that the courts of a specified jurisdiction (for example England and Wales), have exclusive jurisdiction to settle any dispute arising out of or in connection with the agreement.</core:para><core:para>Exclusive jurisdiction clauses are intended to prevent the parties from bringing proceedings against the other in the courts of a jurisdiction other than the one set out in the jurisdiction clause.</core:para><core:para>An exclusive jurisdiction clause provides some certainty to the parties. However, it cannot guarantee that a party will not start proceedings in a different jurisdiction, nor can it be assumed that a court in that other jurisdiction will automatically stay those proceedings or decline jurisdiction.</core:para><core:para>For detailed guidance, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F2349FFF-7B68-44E0-B2F2-2BD6385D6941"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—exclusive jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Non-exclusive jurisdiction clause</core:title><core:para>A non-exclusive jurisdiction clause enables either party to bring proceedings against the other, either in the courts of the jurisdiction set out in the jurisdiction clause, or in the courts of any other country that has jurisdiction. In other words, a party need not bring proceedings in the courts stated to have non-exclusive jurisdiction in the jurisdiction clause.</core:para><core:para>A non-exclusive jurisdiction clause can provide some flexibility to the parties. However, it may result in a party defending proceedings in a jurisdiction where it is likely to be treated unfavourably or be prejudiced in terms of procedure, costs or similar matters.</core:para><core:para>For detailed guidance, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:9244B9EE-27CB-4555-BCCA-23A9F9FE565A"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—non-exclusive jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses</core:title><core:para>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses (also known as unilateral, hybrid or one-way choice of court agreements) are a specific type of jurisdiction clause which set out different requirements for each party to the agreement as to where they may bring proceedings in the event of a dispute. Asymmetric clauses typically provide that one party may only bring proceedings in the courts of a specified jurisdiction, while the other party may bring proceedings in any court that has jurisdiction.</core:para><core:para>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses are typically included in finance documents—the clause is expressed as exclusive, but notwithstanding this, the lender (but not the borrower) is permitted to bring proceedings in any other courts which may have jurisdiction if it chooses. The borrower is therefore obliged to start any proceedings in the chosen jurisdiction while allowing the lender flexibility. Lenders have historically been extremely reluctant to negotiate any changes to this position. However, the enforcement of judgments deriving from asymmetric jurisdiction clauses has been uncertain in some jurisdictions. The practical effect of an asymmetric jurisdiction clause and the ability to enforce a judgment given by court, in reliance of that clause, will depend on which jurisdiction regime applies.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses—Regulation (EU) 1215/2012, Brussels I (recast)</core:title><!--Janna: technically the Brussels regime is this reg plus Brussels I and Brussels Convention as all still apply in some form. I would also note that under the transitional provisions the recast reg is only applied if the proceedings had been commenced prior to 31 December 2025. Given the passage of time it is unlikely this would still be of relevance.I would delete the first para. --><core:para>When interpreting the effect of a jurisdiction clause, the courts of EU Member States are required to apply the provisions in Regulation (EU) 1215/2012, Brussels I (recast). However, historically, their approach to the effect of an asymmetric jurisdiction clause has not been consistent. Most notably, in France, the courts had tended towards the approach that such clauses are invalid.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Societa Italiana Lastre SPA (SIL) v Agora SARL Case C-537/23</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>This inconsistency in approach, throughout the EU, was considered in some detail by the Court of Justice in <core:emph typestyle="it">Societa Italiana Lastre SPA (SIL) v Agora SAR</core:emph> (2025). It held that an asymmetric jurisdiction clause may fall within the regulation. The key findings are that:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>an asymmetric jurisdiction clause means a clause that confers jurisdiction for one party to bring proceedings before a designated court and permits another party to bring proceedings before either that designated court or other competent courts</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the validity of an asymmetric jurisdiction clause (or any jurisdiction clause that might be considered to be imprecise), is to be determined by application of the autonomous criteria set out in Article 25. It is not to be determined by considering criteria that would render the agreement null and void under the national laws of the EU Member State in which proceedings have been commenced. The rationale for this is to ensure that the legal certainty objective of the regulation is met</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>when determining validity:</core:para><core:sub1list type="bullet"><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the designated courts must be courts of either EU Member States or parties to the Lugano Convention 2007—if the clause is so wide that it would encompass other courts ie third states, it will not meet the regulation’s requirement for certainty</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the clause must set out objective factors from which the court seised can ascertain whether it has jurisdiction. These factors must be ‘sufficiently precise’</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the clause must not be contrary to the provisions of Articles 15, 19 or 23 of Brussels I (recast)—such articles, which protect consumers, employees and the insured of an insurance contract, provide for an asymmetric approach to jurisdiction. For guidance, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:32CA4C32-916D-4F50-ACBD-0BC49000DDBC"><lnci:content>Brussels I (recast)—dealing with consumer claims</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:B0323B06-B8B1-4EC5-8D50-BECE36D994A4"><lnci:content>Brussels I (recast)—dealing with insurance matters</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the clause must not derogate from the provisions in Article 24 which provide courts with exclusive jurisdiction in certain circumstances or types of claims. For guidance, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D3F23361-8823-46D2-84E2-3E9E6CE79B33"><lnci:content>Brussels I (recast)—exclusive jurisdiction (art 24)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para></core:sub1listitem></core:sub1list></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For further insight, see News Analyses: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:C3F09EAB-518B-4FD2-9C97-515D3174E81F"><lnci:content>European Court of Justice gives decision on asymmetric jurisdiction clauses (Società Italiana Lastre Spa v Agora SARL)</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:EB650B8E-599D-4F2E-BFD1-86D4ACBE3B1C"><lnci:content>Court of Justice’s first ruling on the conformity of asymmetric jurisdiction clauses with the Brussels I (recast) Regulation and the 2007 Lugano Convention</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>The Loan Market Association (LMA) has updated its German Law Investment Grade and German Law Real Estate Finance Facility Agreements to include a modified asymmetric jurisdiction clause as these documents are directly impacted by the decision in <core:emph typestyle="it">Societa Italiana Lastre SPA (SIL) v Agora SAR</core:emph>.</core:para><core:para>For English law documentation, the modified clause is not directly included; instead, the LMA is preparing a consolidated jurisdiction clause guidance note which is pending publication. The guidance note will provide guidance and include the form of revised asymmetric jurisdiction clause as an option for English law contracts. Prior to the publication of the guidance note, the LMA recommends that those parties who are considering modifying the current form of LMA recommended asymmetric jurisdiction clause, should refer to its German Law Investment Grade and German Law Real Estate Finance Facility Agreements, available to members only on the LMA Documentation Hub.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses—2005 Hague Convention on Choice of Court Agreements</core:title><core:para>The UK government became a member of the <!--Janna: The HCCH link is https://www.hcch.net/en/instruments/conventions/specialised-sections/choice-of-court--><!--NC: Note to editor - please replace the external link with the https address from Janna--><core:url address="www.hcch.net/en/instruments/conventions/specialised-sections/choice-of-court" type="https">2005 Hague Convention on Choice of Court Agreements</core:url> (2005 Hague Convention) in its own right following IP completion day, ie 1 January 2021.</core:para><core:para>However, there is disagreement between the EU and the UK as to whether the 2005 Hague Convention applies to agreements entered into prior to the UK becoming a member in its own right:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>UK’s position—it argues that it should apply to agreements entered into after 1 October 2015, when the 2005 Hague Convention came into force in the UK due to the UK’s membership of the EU</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>EU Commission’s position—it takes the contrary position to that adopted by the UK and has stated that the 2005 Hague Convention will only apply between the EU and the UK to exclusive choice of court agreements concluded after the 2005 Hague Convention entered into force for the UK as a contracting party in its own right</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="juportal.be/content/ECLI:BE:CASS:2025:ARR.20250327.1F.2" type="https">Culturel-Ludique-Divertissement DIST v HORI Limit C.24.0012.E</core:url></fn:margin-note>The application of the 2005 Hague Convention to the UK was considered by the Belgium Supreme Court in <core:emph typestyle="it">Culturel-Ludique-Divertissement DIST v HORI Limit</core:emph> in March 2025. It held that:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the 2005 Hague Convention was applicable for the UK from 1 October 2015 to 31 December 2020 as part of the EU and from 1 January 2021 as a contracting party in its own right</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the 2005 Hague Convention was in force for the UK during the Brexit transition period, ie from 1 February 2020 to 31 December 2020</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>under Article 16(1) (the application of the convention applies to exclusive choice-of-court agreements concluded after its entry into force for the State of the chosen court), the 2005 Hague Convention has applied continuously since 1 October 2015 for the UK</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>While this provides certainty from a UK perspective, it is only binding in Belgium. Other EU Member States may take a different approach.</core:para><core:para>For more information on the decision in this case, see News Analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:AED2F8C7-5B84-4E16-AF74-1037C01970C0"><lnci:content>Belgian Supreme Court upholds the application of the 2005 Hague Convention to exclusive choice of court agreements concluded during the Brexit transition period</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>The 2005 Hague Convention obliges all contracting states to uphold exclusive choice of court agreements in favour of the courts of a contracting state and to enforce the resulting judgment. However, the 2005 Hague Convention expressly provides that it only applies in relation to judgments deriving from exclusive choice of court agreements. It does not apply to asymmetric jurisdiction clauses of the type commonly found in facility agreements and other finance documents. Therefore, the 2005 Hague Convention does not assist with concerns about enforceability of an English judgment when there has been reliance on an asymmetric jurisdiction clause for the court’s jurisdiction.</core:para><core:para>It should be noted that the 2005 Hague Convention is also narrower in application than the Brussels Regime in that it does not extend to claims in tort. It has also been recognised that, while the 2005 Hague Convention allows for the enforcement of non-monetary judgments, this may not be possible under the internal laws of the relevant contracting state. In such cases, the contracting state court is not obliged to enforce the judgment. This would be of relevance, for example, to orders to freeze assets.</core:para><core:para>For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:5477CA44-3276-4534-A984-71AFB14773E7"><lnci:content>Hague Convention on Choice of Court Agreements—jurisdiction</lnci:content></lnci:cite>. For information on the countries for which the convention is in force, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E52B608C-0120-49B3-91F6-C8ADEE92F807"><lnci:content>Tracker—Hague Convention on Choice of Courts Agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses—Hague Convention of July 2019 on the Recognition and Enforcement of Foreign Judgments in Civil or Commercial Matters</core:title><core:para>On 12 January 2024, the UK <core:url address="www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-citizens-and-businesses-to-be-spared-time-and-money-on-cross-border-legal-disputes?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=govuk-notifications-topic&amp;utm_source=11516f9f-3771-4117-b8fa-0b458f498fc9&amp;utm_content=immediately" type="https">signed</core:url> the <!--Janna: The HCCH link is https://www.hcch.net/en/instruments/conventions/full-text/?cid=137--><!--NC: Note to editor - please replace the external link with the https address from Janna--><core:url address="www.hcch.net/en/instruments/conventions/full-text/?cid=137" type="https">2019 Hague Convention</core:url> on the recognition and enforcement of foreign judgments in civil and commercial matters (the Hague Judgments Convention).</core:para><core:para>The convention came into force for the UK on 1 July 2025, being the first day of the month after the expiry of 12 months from the date of ratification (Article 28 of the Hague Judgments Convention); the UK having ratified the Hague Judgments Convention on 27 June 2024, see <core:url address="www.hcch.net/en/news-archive/details/?varevent=985" type="https">HCCH website: UK</core:url>.</core:para><core:para>Initially, the convention will not be in force for the UK’s overseas territories, but the UK Government has stated that it will determine whether it should also be extended to cover them.</core:para><core:para>On 24 May 2024, the Recognition and Enforcement of Judgments (2019 Hague Convention etc) Regulations 2024 (SI 2024/713) were made. These came into force when the Hague Judgments Convention entered into force in respect of the UK (see above). For more information, see News Analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:85B318E8-3458-4AC8-A4E3-F89A963879F0"><lnci:content>Hague Judgments Convention—UK legislation and practice direction now all published</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>The Hague Judgments Convention provides a set of common rules for the recognition and enforcement of civil and commercial judgments between the UK and the other contracting parties. Contracting parties include the EU and the EU Member States. See <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:154C12C2-20E0-45B6-B35A-31D994035DD5"><lnci:content>Tracker—Hague Judgments Convention</lnci:content></lnci:cite> for information on whether a country is a signatory and whether the convention is in force for that country.</core:para><core:para>Importantly for finance lawyers, the Hague Judgments Convention provides for recognition and enforcement of judgments deriving from choice of court agreements other than exclusive choice of court agreements (see Article 5(1)(m) of the Hague Judgments Convention). The <core:url address="www.hcch.net/en/publications-and-studies/details4/?pid=6797" type="https">explanatory report</core:url> on the Hague Judgments Convention specifically confirms that asymmetrical jurisdiction clauses are not considered exclusive under the 2005 Hague Convention and therefore fall within the scope of the Hague Judgments Convention.</core:para><core:para>The Hague Judgments Convention has no retroactive effect. Article 16 of the Hague Judgments Convention makes clear that it can only apply to the recognition and enforcement of a judgment in circumstances where the convention had effect between the relevant states at the time the proceedings that led to that judgment were instituted.</core:para><core:para>For detailed information on the Hague Judgments Convention, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:55D6F6B5-18AF-401E-9682-F913EDE1537D"><lnci:content>Hague Judgments Convention</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and News Analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:C42649C0-E5C4-48A6-9D6A-8FC7B7983B2C"><lnci:content>The Hague Judgments Convention—why is it of interest to finance lawyers?</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Key considerations for jurisdiction provisions in finance documentation post-Brexit</core:title><core:para>Following the UK leaving the EU, and the impact this had on the application of Brussels I (recast) when interpreting jurisdiction clauses, some parties changed their approach to the type of jurisdiction clauses they used ie they looked at including a two-way exclusive jurisdiction clause, rather than the usual asymmetric jurisdiction clause in finance documents, given that such a clause would fall within the remit of the 2005 Hague Convention. This meant that the choice of the English courts and any judgment they gave would be recognised by EU Member States and other countries for which the 2005 Hague Convention is in force. Clearly, however, this involves a loss of flexibility for finance parties and so they may first wish to consider whether such a step is necessary. For example, the position under the laws of the particular jurisdiction may be that an English judgment would be enforced under the local law in any event.</core:para><core:para>The fact that the Hague Judgments Convention is now in force in the UK should also be considered, although note, as mentioned above, it does not have retroactive effect.</core:para><core:para>The LMA’s November 2020 Brexit Note (consolidated version), available to members on the LMA website, contains a list of factors that parties should consider prior to including a two-way exclusive jurisdiction clause in finance documentation. It suggests considering the following:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the importance of the potential enforceability of an English judgment in any given EU Member State in the context of the relevant transaction—eg enforcement of an English judgment in an EU Member State may not be considered sufficiently important if the transaction is sufficiently secured or if there are no significant assets located in that EU Member State</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the extent to which a future English judgment could be enforced in the relevant EU Member State pursuant to its local law—local law advice is likely to be needed for this</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>If enforceability is considered important AND there is doubt over enforceability of an English judgment under the local law, then the following need to be considered:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the extent to which use of the flexibility afforded by an asymmetric exclusive jurisdiction clause to bring proceedings in the courts of that EU Member State would be a viable approach</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>whether a two-way exclusive jurisdiction clause should be used in place of a one-sided exclusive jurisdiction clause, looking at:</core:para><core:sub1list type="bullet"><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the extent to which enforcement of a judgment in that EU Member State pursuant to the local law of that EU Member State is materially more difficult than the enforcement in that EU Member State of an English judgment on a two-way exclusive jurisdiction clause pursuant to the 2005 Hague Convention, and</core:para></core:sub1listitem><core:sub1listitem><core:para>the extent to which any benefits attached to a potentially more straightforward enforcement in that EU Member State of an English judgment on a two-way exclusive jurisdiction clause pursuant to the 2005 Hague Convention outweigh the flexibility of including an asymmetric exclusive jurisdiction clause</core:para></core:sub1listitem></core:sub1list></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>whether another form of dispute resolution, such as arbitration (see: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E4F83CAD-CF3B-4ACC-9077-C0231D741060" citeref="CITEID_110859"><lnci:content>Arbitration clauses</lnci:content></lnci:cite> below) would be more appropriate</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>Another possibility would be to use a jurisdiction clause providing for a country other than England and Wales.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1087311">Service of process and process agents</core:title><core:para>The general rule is that proceedings commenced in the courts of England and Wales must be served within the jurisdiction (ie England and Wales) (CPR 6.6)</core:para><core:para>Serving proceedings on a foreign borrower outside of the jurisdiction can be problematic because:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the lender will want to act quickly—serving proceedings outside of the jurisdiction can be a lengthy process depending on the country in which the proceedings are to be served</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the lender will want to avoid any uncertainty—permission of the court to serve outside the jurisdiction may be required (CPR 6.36) and there is no guarantee that permission will be granted. Permission is not required if the provisions in CPR 6.33 are met which includes when the parties have entered into an exclusive choice of court agreement conferring jurisdiction on the English courts and the court has the power under the convention to determine the claim</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the lender will want to keep costs down—additional legal fees will be incurred in relation to making the application for permission to serve outside of the jurisdiction and instructing local practitioners to actually serve in the relevant local jurisdiction</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>It is possible for parties to agree in a contract a particular method or place of service, in the event of a claim being started in relation to that contract (CPR 6.11).</core:para><core:para>This is useful in relation to foreign borrowers where it is usual to provide in the finance documents that service can be made on the borrower through a process agent at a specific address in England and Wales. A process agent is a party that is appointed to receive, accept and acknowledge service of process on behalf of another party. However, care should be taken in the drafting of a clause dealing with the appointment of an agent for service of process. Although such a clause does not of itself confer jurisdiction, it has been found to amount to a submission to the non-exclusive jurisdiction of the courts in the place to which it relates. An agreement should always include a clear jurisdiction clause and a separate clause appointing an agent for service of process, if appropriate. Example judgments considering this issue are:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Deutsche Bank AG v Sebastian Holdings Inc [2009] EWHC 2132 (Comm) at paras [81]–[83]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><core:emph typestyle="it">Deutsche Bank AG v Sebastian Holdings Inc</core:emph>—an Equities Prime Brokerage Agreement contained an agent for service of process clause. As to whether it conferred jurisdiction was considered to be a factual matter. It was held that ‘if the parties express arrangements as to jurisdiction were not intended to confer jurisdiction in relation to a dispute, then the service of process clause cannot have been intended to bring about a different result’</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Cinnamon European Structured Credit Master Fund v Banco Commercial Portugues SA [2009] EWHC 3381 (Ch) at para [37] onwards</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><core:emph typestyle="it">Cinnamon European Structured Credit Master Fund v Banco Commercial Portugues SA</core:emph>—it was held that a clause headed Agent for Services of Process, set out in a Representation letter was in reality a jurisdiction clause</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For an example process agent appointment letter, see Precedent: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editdraft:2EC56C86-ED90-48A6-AEC4-8DB02BA1C837"><lnci:content>Appointment of process agent letter: for a bilateral facility agreement</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>It is usual for the definition of finance documents in a process agent appointment letter to cover the existing documentation and any future documentation in relation to the transaction. Appointing a process agent in relation to all finance documents (existing and future) will avoid the need to reappoint the agent in respect of any future finance documents which are entered into.</core:para><core:para>Finance documents should ideally include a mechanism for the replacement of the process agent if, for any reason, the process agent is unable to act as agent for service of process.</core:para><!--21.10.25 AI--><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regera Sàrl v Cohen [2025] EWHC 2107 (Comm)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>The Commercial Court in <core:emph typestyle="it">Regera Sàrl v Cohen</core:emph> held that default judgments obtained after serving proceedings on a replacement process agent were invalid because the lender’s unilateral right to appoint that agent was unfair under Consumer Rights Act 2015. The clause—drawn from standard LMA-style wording—gave the lender sole power to replace the service agent if the original ceased to act. Applied to individual guarantors, the court found this created a significant imbalance and failed the statutory fairness test. As a result, service was defective, and the defendants were entitled to have judgment set aside under CPR 13.2.</core:para><core:para>The decision highlights the need to give particular consideration to any standard process agent provisions, especially where any obligor is an individual. Clauses should avoid unilateral lender powers, ensure transparency, and require clear notice and consent for replacements. In particular, consider including an express obligation to notify all parties of any change in process agent in the documentation. More broadly, lenders should not assume service on an agent will always be upheld, especially in mixed consumer/corporate deals. The current LMA drafting, which has been drafted for use in the sophisticated commercial lending sector, does not always meet this standard and so the drafting will need to be considered where individuals are involved.</core:para><!--21.10.25 AI end--></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_110859">Arbitration clauses</core:title><core:para>In cross-border transactions, it will be necessary to obtain foreign legal advice on the jurisdiction of the borrower. This should include a confirmation on whether a judgment obtained from an English court against the borrower would be enforceable in the foreign jurisdiction without a retrial of the merits of the case. This is important where the majority of the assets of the borrower are located in a foreign jurisdiction.</core:para><core:para>Where a judgment from an English court would not be enforceable against the borrower in the relevant foreign jurisdiction without a retrial of the merits of the case, consider choosing arbitration to resolve disputes instead.</core:para><core:para>Arbitration awards are enforceable in some countries without a retrial of the merits of the case under the Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards adopted by the United Nations Conference on International Commercial Arbitration on 10 June 1958 (known as the New York Convention). There will need to be reciprocity ie the state in which the enforcement is sought has made a declaration under Article 1.3 to recognise awards in other contracting states only. It will be necessary to obtain written legal advice from legal advisers in the relevant foreign jurisdiction to confirm whether an arbitration award rendered in one country would be enforceable in the foreign jurisdiction against the borrower without a retrial of the merits of the case. For guidance, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D4105733-09AE-4F00-BEA2-FC128BA26976"><lnci:content>The New York Convention—the recognition and enforcement of arbitral awards—an introduction</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>The above issues also apply to any overseas guarantor or other obligor.</core:para><core:para>Lenders usually want as much flexibility and control as possible in terms of whether disputes are resolved in the courts or by arbitration. Where it is desirable to include an arbitration clause in a finance document, this is usually done by granting the lender the option to either go to court or arbitrate. The borrower would not have the same option. In all cases, foreign legal advice should be obtained on jurisdiction clauses, arbitration clauses and how they work together.</core:para><core:para>If the parties to the finance documents wish to have the option to settle disputes by way of arbitration, an arbitration clause will need to be included in the finance documents:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>Common clauses—such clauses are often used and provide that either party can require that a dispute be arbitrated</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>Unilateral clauses—the parties may agree that only one of them will have the ability to choose to resolve a dispute by arbitration and such clauses do appear in finance transactions</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>Multi-tiered clauses—parties wishing to provide for procedures aimed at resolving the dispute before it is submitted to arbitration should insert a multi-tiered clause. Examples of procedures that may be required prior to a dispute being arbitrated include mediation or expert determination</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>Hybrid clauses—in some circumstances, parties may agree that certain disputes should be referred to arbitration while others should be dealt with by litigation or expert determination</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><tr:secsub1><core:title>Types of arbitration</core:title><core:para>The two main arbitration institutions which are referred to in arbitration clauses in English law finance documents are:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.lcia.org/">LCIA website</core:url></fn:margin-note>the London Court of International Arbitration (LCIA) under the LCIA Arbitration Rules, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="iccwbo.org/dispute-resolution-services/arbitration/" type="http">ICC International Court of Arbitration</core:url></fn:margin-note>the International Chamber of Commerce (ICC) under the ICC Arbitration Rules</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For both ICC and LCIA arbitrations in relation to disputes under finance documents governed by English law, lenders will usually want to ensure that the finance documents include appropriate arbitration provisions to provide that:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the law applicable to the substantive merits of the dispute will be English law</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the seat of the arbitration will be England—the seat determines the procedural law which will apply to the arbitration, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the proceedings will be conducted in English</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Arbitration Acts</core:emph></core:para><core:para>The Arbitration Act 1996 (AA 1996) sets out the rules when dealing with arbitration proceedings seated in England and Wales (as well as Northern Ireland). This act has been pivotal in boosting London-seated arbitrations, such as the LCIA. A new Arbitration Act 2025 (AA 2025), not yet in force, amends the AA 1996 and reinforces London’s status as a leading seat for arbitration. For information on the in force date of the AA 2025, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:903DCA48-E586-43E9-8B65-A494419781B7"><lnci:content>When will the Arbitration Act 2025 come into force?</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Enka Insaat Ve Sanayi A.S v OOO Insurance Company Chubb [2020] UKSC 38</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>AA 2025 introduces several key enhancements including a new default rule on the governing law of the arbitration agreement (the <core:emph typestyle="it">lex arbitri</core:emph>), removing the common law rule as decided by the Supreme Court in <core:emph typestyle="it">Enka v Chubb</core:emph> (where absent an express agreement, the law of the contract containing the arbitration agreement applies) and replacing it with a default rule that where absent an express agreement, the law of the seat will be the <core:emph typestyle="it">lex arbitri</core:emph>.</core:para><core:para>For more information, see News Analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:C4F73C73-554D-456B-AC71-48B16E7421FE"><lnci:content>Arbitration Bill receives Royal Assent, strengthening England and Wales as an arbitration hub</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para>In addition, parties may also wish to agree provisions relating to confidentiality, appointment of arbitrators and costs. For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F6D7654F-7E1C-494F-8EDB-FCCDD155BA56"><lnci:content>Arbitration agreements—content</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Jurisdiction of an arbitral tribunal</core:emph></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Barclays Bank plc v VEB.RF [2024] EWHC 3088 (Comm)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>The jurisdiction of an arbitral tribunal may be considered by the English courts under the AA 1996. In some cases, the English courts may determine that the arbitral tribunal does not have jurisdiction to determine the dispute between the parties. This will be specific to the facts of the case but an example can be seen in <core:emph typestyle="it">Barclays Bank plc v VEB. RF</core:emph>. The court determined that the notice served by Barclays (the claimant) requiring VEB.RF (the defendant) to withdraw the arbitration and commence proceedings in the English courts was valid under clause 13(b)(ii) and (iii) of the contractual agreement between the parties. The court ruled that the defendant's arguments of formal invalidity and waiver/estoppel regarding the claimant's exercise of its contractual right under clause 13(b)(ii) were unsubstantiated.</core:para><core:para>The court granted the claimant declarations that the arbitral tribunal constituted under the LCIA rules had no jurisdiction to determine the dispute between the parties that had arisen under a currency swap agreement, and allowed the claimant's application to vary the terms of the final anti-suit injunction granted earlier. For more information, see News Analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:72C4B03A-DD1E-4F2E-AC50-A4D0C5C8A4DD"><lnci:content>English court declares Arbitral Tribunal has no jurisdiction to hear dispute (Barclays Bank plc v VEB)</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain></kh:body><kh:related-content type="further-reading"><kh:references ref-type="further-reading"><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Governing law, ungovernable questions: the challenge of public international law in the World Bank's development policy financing agreements (2025) 9 JIBFL 653</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Drafting on the edge: ambiguity in hybrid jurisdiction clauses (2025) 9 JIBFL 656</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>A Brexit re-set? How will the UK's accession to the 2019 Hague Convention impact English legal opinions? (2025) 7 JIBFL 491</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Cross-border privilege (2025) 5 JIBFL 333</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses: when will they be effective? (2025) 5 JIBFL 310</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>How easy is it to enforce English judgments in the EU post-Brexit? A look at the procedures in Italy, Germany and Spain (2021) 5 JIBFL 354</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Brexit and dispute resolution clauses: the options for finance parties (2021) 2 JIBFL 109</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Drafting for Brexit in finance documents (2020) 11 JIBFL 727</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Exclusive jurisdiction agreements post-transition (2020) 10 JIBFL 709</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Dispute resolution choices for banks and financial institutions in a post-Brexit world: opting for arbitration? (2019) 9 JIBFL 614</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The continuing effect of the Hague Convention on Choice of Court Agreements post-Brexit (2019) 9 JIBFL 571</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Why English law as the governing law of contracts? (2019) 7 JIBFL 427</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>How does German law interpret English law terminology in German law contracts? (2019) 3 JIBFL 182</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The strengthening of jurisdiction agreements following Brussels Reg (Recast) and the impact of Brexit (2017) 8 JIBFL 476</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Ensuring that your Jurisdiction Clause Ensures Exclusive Jurisdiction (2015) 7 JIBFL 453</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The recast Judgments Regulation: imminent reform of the rules of jurisdiction and enforcement of foreign judgments in the EU (2014) 11 JIBFL 709</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements, declarations, damages and compatibility with Regulation 44/2001 (2014) 11 JIBFL 705</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Are you being served? The Supreme Court's pragmatic approach to alternative service out of the jurisdiction (2013) 10 JIBFL 651</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Asymmetric jurisdiction clauses and intercreditor disputes: a case of too much flexibility? (2013) 7 JIBFL 424</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Stormy skies: uncovering the problems of s 8 of the Contracts (Rights of Third Parties) Act 1999 (2013) 7 JIBFL 421</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Legal Ease with Lexis®PSL Banking &amp; Finance: Jurisdiction clauses in loan documentation (2013) 4 JIBFL 252</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction clauses: A French setback for party autonomy (2013) 4 JIBFL 199</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>A principled approach to choice of law in contract? (2013) 3 JIBFL 151</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The recast Brussels I Regulation: an end to Italian torpedoes and greater certainty for choice of jurisdiction? (2013) 3 JIBFL 169</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Demystifying the use of arbitration clauses in international finance documents (2012) 6 JIBFL 357</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Anti-suit injunctions and a touch of egoistic paternalism (2012) 5 JIBFL 304</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Suing insolvent banks: can parties preserve their choice of jurisdiction? (2012) 4 JIBFL 230</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Sovereign immunity and enforcing foreign adverse judgments in England (2011) 9 JIBFL 573</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Your place or mine? The ECJ brings clarity to the rules on jurisdiction (2011) 8 JIBFL 500</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Financial transactions in the crossfire of Rome II (2011) 1 JIBFL 25</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Competing Jurisdiction Clauses (2010) 9 JIBFL 551</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The applicability of jurisdiction clauses where the underlying contract is void (2009) 7 JIBFL 408</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para></kh:references></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="related-documents"><!--Overview--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:7450A454-1437-4A3D-A351-8A41DBD56922"><lnci:content>The facility agreement—overview</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Practice Notes--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:21E81B9B-D45D-4A87-A09F-12AEF25CC782"><lnci:content>Applicable law—a guide for dispute resolution practitioners</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:514F7713-2714-4580-BD0B-2ADCBE2286C2"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—introduction</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3987F0A7-EC9A-4C7A-A574-C13C09FE2651"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—asymmetric jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F2349FFF-7B68-44E0-B2F2-2BD6385D6941"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—exclusive jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:9244B9EE-27CB-4555-BCCA-23A9F9FE565A"><lnci:content>Jurisdiction agreements—non-exclusive jurisdiction agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:EA0F39C5-85FE-4FAC-A818-FEEF9579993B"><lnci:content>Challenging court jurisdiction—general principles</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:F6D7654F-7E1C-494F-8EDB-FCCDD155BA56"><lnci:content>Arbitration agreements—content</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:903DCA48-E586-43E9-8B65-A494419781B7"><lnci:content>When will the Arbitration Act 2025 come into force?</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E52B608C-0120-49B3-91F6-C8ADEE92F807"><lnci:content>Tracker—Hague Convention on Choice of Courts Agreements</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:154C12C2-20E0-45B6-B35A-31D994035DD5"><lnci:content>Tracker—Hague Judgments Convention</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D4105733-09AE-4F00-BEA2-FC128BA26976"><lnci:content>The New York Convention—the recognition and enforcement of arbitral awards—an introduction</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Precedent--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editdraft:2EC56C86-ED90-48A6-AEC4-8DB02BA1C837"><lnci:content>Appointment of process agent letter: for a bilateral facility agreement</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--CPR references--><lnci:cite><lnci:content>CPR 6.6, CPR 6.11, CPR 6.36</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--NA--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:A8906373-3AE8-48AB-BCBD-173456020F7D"><lnci:content>What does Brexit mean for dispute resolution in England and Wales?</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:E6D8B181-E01F-4697-9AE6-59F06D4D2A20"><lnci:content>One way jurisdiction clauses—governing law and interpretation (Mauritius Commercial Bank v Hestia Holdings)</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:0A90BC42-D482-482D-9425-6CADA0379948"><lnci:content>Brexit—impact on governing law and jurisdiction regimes for R&amp;I lawyers</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Lexology--><lnci:cite normcite="LexPan, DISPUTE RESOLUTION, FULL" type="comm"><lnci:content>Lexology Panoramic: Dispute Resolution</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="LexPan, ENFORCEMENT OF FOREIGN JUDGMENTS, FULL" type="comm"><lnci:content>Lexology Panoramic: Enforcement of Foreign Judgments</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="external-links"><core:url address="www.lcia.org/">London Court of International Arbitration (LCIA)</core:url><core:url address="iccwbo.org/dispute-resolution-services/arbitration/" type="http">International Chamber of Commerce (ICC) International Court of Arbitration</core:url><core:url address="www.lma.eu.com" type="http">Loan Market Association website</core:url><core:url address="www.treasurers.org/LMA-guide-2017">ACT Borrower’s Guide to the LMA’s Investment Grade Agreements (2017)</core:url><core:url address="www.fmlc.org/paper-on-asymmetric-jurisdiction-clauses.html">Issues of Legal Uncertainty Arising in the Context of Asymmetric Jurisdiction Clauses</core:url></kh:related-content></kh:document>