<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "\\voyager\templates\DTDs\LNUK\KnowHow\KnowHow.dtd"><?Pub EntList mdash reg #8364 #176 #169 #8230 #10003 #x2610 #x2611 #x2612 #x2613?><kh:document xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core" xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn" xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/header" xmlns:kh="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/kh" xmlns:lnb="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/lnb" xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci" xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr" xmlns:atict="http://www.arbortext.com/namespace/atict"><atict:info tracking="on" ref="3" print="" color="" /><atict:user user="jimened2" fullname="Jimenez, Steven (REPH-ILO)" color="#909000" /><atict:user user="varmap" fullname="" color="#00A0A0" /><atict:user user="CampbM" fullname="Campbell, Miranda E. (LNG-LON)" color="#D06000" /><atict:user user="SMITHA7" fullname="Smith, Antony J. (LNG-LON)" color="maroon" /><atict:user user="jahodovs" fullname="" color="#8000FF" /><kh:body><kh:document-title>Energy derivatives</kh:document-title><kh:mini-summary>This Practice Note provides an overview of the use of derivatives in the energy markets and looks at divergence in the regulation of energy derivatives in the EU and the UK.</kh:mini-summary><core:para>This Practice Note provides an overview of the use of derivatives in the energy markets and looks at divergence in the regulation of energy derivatives in the EU and the UK.</core:para><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164608">What are energy derivatives?</core:title><core:para>Energy derivatives reference the underlying price of an energy source, such as oil, gas or electricity. They can be traded <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1528526" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:476F1E1F-D486-46DA-8295-2B1FDD4A4B94"><lnci:content>over-the-counter</lnci:content></lnci:cite> (OTC) or on an exchange (exchange traded derivatives or ETDs). Participants in the energy derivatives markets include: </core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>brokers</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>financial institutions</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>investment funds</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>speculators, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>direct energy users</core:para></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164609">Common types of energy derivatives</core:title><tr:secsub1><core:title>Forwards/futures</core:title><core:para>A forward contract in the energy markets is an OTC derivative contract that provides for the future delivery of an energy product, but with the price of that delivery agreed on the date of the contract. A futures contract is broadly similar but is traded on an exchange rather than privately negotiated with a market counterparty. See Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:8690A9D3-635D-40A5-81B5-1A23D4C4CA7B"><lnci:content>Types of derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite> for more information on these products.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Swaps and contracts for differences</core:title><core:para>A swap contract in the energy markets is usually cash settled—they are frequently entered into with financial institutions. A user of a commodity such as oil that wants to protect itself against rising prices may agree to pay a fixed price for oil to a financial institution and the financial institution will agree to pay the spot price (the current market price) of oil on a certain date.</core:para><core:para>Alternatively, a user of energy which believes that market prices may fall may agree to pay the financial institution the market price of oil and receive a fixed payment. This 'swap' arrangement will run for a defined period of time with regular payment dates—such as each month of each quarter of a year until it expires at the 'expiry date'.</core:para><core:para>A variant of this arrangement is a contract for differences (CFD), whereby the parties will agree to pay the difference in the spot price of an energy commodity on the start date of a contract and the price of the maturity date of that contract. Which of the parties is required to pay will depend on whether the spot price on maturity is higher or lower than that at the outset of the contract.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Options</core:title><core:para>The purchase of an option contract gives the buyer the right, but not the obligation, to buy an energy commodity from the counterparty, or to sell it to the counterparty. For example, if a company enters into an option contract for the right to buy a certain number of barrels of oil with a market counterparty, the price of that purchase will be agreed at the outset, as with a forward or futures contract. </core:para><core:para>However, the company is not obliged to actually make that purchase and so may decline to exercise the option, particularly if the spot price of oil at the option exercise date is cheaper than that agreed under the option contract. The price of entry into an option contract is a premium, which is a small percentage of the notional value of the contract. In declining to exercise that option, the company will lose only the non-returnable premium amount.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Cash settlement</core:title><core:para>Energy derivatives can provide for either the physical delivery of the underlying energy commodity or a cash settlement amount. The two types of settlement are suitable for different types of market participants. For example, a manufacturing company may have a requirement for 1,000 barrels of oil on a specified date or in a specified period. As an alternative to entering into a direct purchase in the energy markets at the time the oil is needed, it might enter into a forward contract for physical delivery of 1,000 barrels at a set price and on a set date. On the date agreed, the barrels will be due for delivery. A financial institution which operates in energy markets has no need for barrels of oil but can enter a contract on a cash settlement basis. In doing this, it can receive the cash difference between the price of oil at the outset and the price of oil at the date of payment under the forward contract. If the price of the oil increases, its counterparty will pay a cash sum representing the difference between the two prices.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164610">Uses and users of energy derivatives</core:title><core:para>There are a number of uses and types of user of energy derivatives. Energy derivatives are part of the global energy markets users of energy such as transport companies, airlines and power companies can use energy derivatives for the purposes of protecting themselves from adverse price movements. Speculators also take positions on particular energy sources, increase overall market liquidity. Additionally, along with other commodities, energy products form part of many mixed portfolios for institutional and individual investors.</core:para><tr:secsub1><core:title>Direct users of energy</core:title><core:para>To take the example of an airline, one of its principal costs is aviation fuel, which will be closely linked to the price of oil. Since the price of fuel is subject to frequent fluctuations, airlines have to manage the risk of changes in the price of fuel and they do this by a combination of outright purchases and derivatives. For example, a forward contract for the purchase of fuel allows the airline, through agreement with a market counterparty, to agree a set price for future delivery of fuel covered by the contract. The risk of a forward contract is however that the forward price is actually more expensive than the spot price open at the time of delivery.</core:para><core:para>In addition to contracting for physical delivery of fuel in a financial derivative contract, an airline can hedge its exposures to the cost of fuel through a cash-settled derivative. This means that it can protect itself against a rise in the price of fuel by entering into a derivative with a financial institution. Any pay-out from the financial institution on this contract will match the extra cost of the fuel which they need to buy.</core:para><core:para>One of the major challenges to any users of energy is to ensure that the amount it spends on that product remains proportionate to its income. As a result, derivatives can provide a degree of certainty through the transfer of risk by way of a derivative contract. For example, in agreeing a forward contract with a financial institution, a user of electricity is buying certainty and removing the risk, of the price it will pay to purchase a key commodity for its business. A company may not always beat the market pricing by using derivatives but they are at least able to obtain certainty as to what the cost of their energy for a particular period will be.</core:para><core:para>In addition, derivatives can also be used to protect parties involved in the energy markets against falls in prices. For example, where the price of gas is volatile, a fall in price may be damaging to a seller of gas and that risk can be removed through a derivative which takes a short position on gas and which will provide a cash payment to compensate for the fall in price.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Speculators</core:title><core:para>Frequent price fluctuations and the depth of the global energy markets are welcome to those looking to earn a return on speculation on energy prices. A speculator might be described as a party which has no direct interest in, or need for, an energy commodity, other than as a means of generating financial gain. As such, speculators have come under frequent criticism as to whether or not they are responsible for the distortion of the energy markets. Cash settled derivatives are valuable tools for speculation since they allow a party to take a position in the energy markets without the need to deal with physical delivery of a commodity. They are also a cost effective method of gaining an exposure to an energy commodity since they do not require the same level of financial outlay that a physical purchase of an asset would require. For example, an option contract can be agreed for a premium payment which will be a small percentage of the full value of the notional amount of the contract.</core:para><core:para>Speculators argue that their willingness to take a position in a market allows genuine users of energy products a range of options in managing the risks associated with their businesses. For example, where an energy producer is looking to hedge itself against a fall in energy prices, a speculator is willing to enter into a contract because it holds a contrary view that prices will rise. This adds liquidity to the market. Others, including financial regulators and government agencies, link the involvement of speculators in markets to high prices, particularly where strong positions are abused.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>Investment portfolios</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.spglobal.com/spdji/en/indices/equity/dow-jones-us-oil-gas-index/#overview" type="https">Dow Jones U.S. Oil &amp; Gas Index</core:url></fn:margin-note>Volatility in the cost of energy has led investment managers to take positions in energy markets through financial derivatives with a view to increasing the performance of their investment portfolios. This can also be achieved through the investment in an index such as the Dow Jones U.S. Oil &amp; Gas Index or using products such as exchange traded funds, which may consist of a basket of energy products.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164611">Regulation of energy derivatives</core:title><tr:secsub1><core:title>EU EMIR and UK EMIR—definition of derivative contract</core:title><core:para>Regulation (EU) 648/2012 (EU EMIR) is the principal EU measure applying to derivatives, including certain energy derivatives. The UK version of EU EMIR, Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012 (UK EMIR) applies in the UK.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 648/2012, art 2(5)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012, art 2(5)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, Annex I, Section C</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Regulated Activities) Order 2001, SI 2001/544, Sch 2</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>EU EMIR, applies to all ‘derivative contracts’. A ‘derivative contract’ is defined in art 2(5) of EU EMIR as a financial instrument set out in points (4) to (10) of Section C of Annex I to the Markets in Financial Instruments Directive 2014/65/EU (MiFID II). In relation to energy derivatives, the relevant points in Section C are (5), (6) and (7), which refer to:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>options, futures, swaps, forwards and any other derivative contracts relating to commodities that must be settled in cash or may be settled in cash at the option of one of the parties other than by reason of default or other termination event</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>options, futures, swaps and any other derivative contract relating to commodities that can be physically settled provided that they are traded on a regulated market, a multi-lateral trading facility (MTF) or an organised trading facility (OTF), except for wholesale energy products traded on an OTF that must be physically settled</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>options, futures, swaps, forwards and any other derivative contracts relating to commodities, that can be physically settled not otherwise mentioned above and not being for commercial purposes, which have the characteristics of other derivative financial instruments</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>Article 2(5) of UK EMIR defines ‘derivative contract’ by reference to corresponding provisions in Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Regulated Activities) Order 2001 (RAO), SI 2001/544, Sch 2 Pt 1, paras 4–10, with differences in the treatment of EU and UK trading venues.</core:para><core:para>For more information on requirements which may be applicable to energy derivatives in certain circumstances under EU EMIR and UK EMIR, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:2B9420AB-A9F9-4983-8E08-12B1DCD6D997"><lnci:content>EU EMIR—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:CFA46F96-3521-45E3-AAB2-0E8A06236592"><lnci:content>UK EMIR—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>MiFID II, EU MiFIR and UK MiFIR</core:title><core:para>The principle measures regulating commodity derivatives (including energy derivatives) in the EU are MiFID II and the Markets in Financial Instruments Regulation (EU) 600/2014 (EU MiFIR). In the UK, the regulatory regime for commodity derivatives is derived from MiFID II and partially contained in the UK version of EU MiFIR, Assimilated Regulation (EU) 600/2014 (UK MiFIR). As explained below, substantial reforms to the UK regime have effect from 6 July 2026 and 1 January 2027.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Definition of commodity derivatives (which include energy derivatives)—EU</core:emph></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 600/2014, art 2(1)(30)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, Annex I, Schedule C</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, art 4(1)(44)(c)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>For the purposes of MiFID II and EU MiFIR, 'commodity derivatives' are derivatives (using the same definition as EU EMIR) linked to commodities and cash settled commodities-linked securities.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Definition of commodity derivatives (which include energy derivatives)—UK</core:emph></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 600/2014, art 2(1)(30)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Regulated Activities) Order 2001, SI 2001/544, Sch 2</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>UK MiFIR defines 'commodity derivatives' as derivatives (using the same definition as UK EMIR) linked to commodities and cash settled commodities-linked securities.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Trading in commodity derivatives as an ancillary activity— EU</core:emph></core:para><core:para>MiFID II requires EU persons trading in commodity (or other) derivatives to be authorised as investment firms, unless an exemption applies.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, art 2(1)(j)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>Under Article 2(1)(j) of MiFID II, persons trading in the EU in commodity derivatives as an ancillary activity are exempt from the requirement to be authorised. Other conditions apply: to benefit from the exemption, the person trading must not be part of a group whose main business is to provide investment services, carry on banking activities or act as a market maker for commodity derivatives; must not use a high-frequency algorithmic trading technique; and must report the basis on which they have assessed that their trading activity is ancillary to their main business if requested by their competent authority.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2021/1833, arts 2–5</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>Criteria for establishing when an activity is to be considered to be ancillary are set out in Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2021/1833. Trading is considered to be ancillary if any one of the following conditions is met:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>trading of cash settled commodity derivatives, excluding ETDs, is below an annual threshold of €3bn</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>trading accounts for 50% or less of the total of the other trading activities of the group</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>capital employed for carrying out commodity derivatives trading accounts for not more than 50% of the capital employed at group level for carrying out the group’s main business</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Trading in commodity derivatives as an ancillary activity—UK</core:emph></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Commission Delegated Assimilated Regulation (EU) 2017/592, art 3</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>In the UK, Commission Delegated Assimilated Regulation (EU) 2017/592 (UK RTS 20) specifies when an activity will be considered ancillary to the main business, known as the ‘ancillary activities test’ (AAT). The AAT has two components—the market share test (suspended by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) pending effectiveness of the reform of the AAT) and the main business test (trading activity must not account for more than 10% of total group trading activity and capital employed must not account for more than 10% of group capital employed).</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.fca.org.uk/publication/policy/ps25-24.pdf">PS25/24 Ancillary Activities Test</core:url></fn:margin-note>With effect from 1 January 2027, the AAT is replaced by three separate and independent tests: a new fixed monetary annual threshold test (£3bn) and modified versions of the trading and capital employed tests forming part of the main business test but with the threshold set at 50%. Firms will be able to rely on the ancillary activity exemption if they meet the conditions of any one of the tests.</core:para><core:para>For more information, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1668849" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Ancillary activities test (AAT)</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1511767" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Reform of the UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1382676" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:DB715D8E-82C6-4F8B-9C7C-344CBA3F96B0"><lnci:content>MiFID and non-MiFID business—What are the MiFID II exemptions?</lnci:content></lnci:cite>—<core:emph typestyle="it"><core:emph typestyle="it">Ancillary business</core:emph></core:emph>.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Position limits, management controls and reporting— EU</core:emph></core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, art 57</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>MiFID II requires Member States to impose position limits on the size of a net position which a person can hold in agricultural commodity derivatives and critical or significant commodity derivatives traded on trading venues and economically equivalent OTC (EEOTC) contracts. There are exemptions for hedging transactions, transactions undertaken to fulfil obligations to provide liquidity on a trading venue and securitised derivatives. Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2022/1302 sets out the methodology for the calculation and application of position limits.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, art 57</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>Trading venues which trade commodity derivatives are required to apply position management controls.</core:para><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU, art 58</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Article 1(11) Directive (EU) 2024/790</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>MiFID II (as amended by Directive (EU) 2024/790 (the MiFID II Review)) requires trading venues to publish weekly reports of the aggregated positions held and provide competent authorities with a complete breakdown of positions on a daily basis. Members or participants of trading venues must provide those trading venues with daily breakdowns of their positions and those of their clients and investment firms trading in commodity derivatives outside a trading venue, must provide competent authorities with similar information. In each case, details must also be provided of the holdings of their clients’ clients, until the end client is reached.</core:para><core:para>For more information, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3E00C247-2B7E-467C-A682-EBA4ECCC0146"><lnci:content>EU MiFID II—commodity derivatives—position limits</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:1D8F4819-72E5-4612-A1A3-CE8BA2ECEC3D"><lnci:content>Position reporting under EU MiFID II</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><core:para><core:emph typestyle="bf">Position limits, management controls and reporting—UK</core:emph></core:para><core:para>Until 6 July 2026:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>MAR 10.2.1 G(2)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>the FCA establishes and applies position limits in line with the methodology set out in Commission Delegated Assimilated Regulation (EU) 2017/591</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Recognition Requirements Regulations, SI 2001/995, Sch Pt I, para 7BA</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>positions management controls requirements for UK regulated markets are set out in paragraph 7BA of Part 1 of the Schedule to the Recognition Requirements Regulations, SI 2001/995</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>MAR 10.3.3R</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>position management controls requirements for trading venue operators of multilateral trading facilities (MTFs) or organised trading facilities (OTFs) are set out in MAR 10.3.3R in the FCA Handbook</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Schedule to the Recognition Requirements Regulations, SI 2001/995, Sch Pt I, para 7BB</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>position reporting requirements for regulated markets are set out in paragraph 7BB of Part 1 of the Schedule to SI 2001/995</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>MAR 10.4.3 R, MAR 10.4.3 AR, MAR 10.4.4 R</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>position reporting requirements for UK firms and UK branches of third country investment firms operating an MTF or OTF are set out in MAR 10.4.3 R, MAR 10.4.3 AR and MAR 10.4.4 R in the FCA Handbook, and</core:para></core:listitem><?Pub Caret -1?><core:listitem><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>MAR 10.4.8D</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>position reporting requirements for investment firms trading OTC are set out in MAR 10.4.8D in the FCA Handbook</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>The reforms set out in FCA <core:url address="www.fca.org.uk/publication/policy/ps25-1.pdf">Policy Statement PS25/1 Reforming the commodity derivatives regulatory framework</core:url> take effect on 6 July 2026. In summary:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>the principal responsibility for setting position limits is transferred from the FCA to trading venues</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>position limits apply only to certain commodity derivatives contracts: the FCA will identify a set of ‘critical’ contracts for which disorderly trading would have the greatest impact on commodity markets and their users and trading venues will set position limits for this narrow set of critical contracts and also extend the application of the position limit regime to contracts that are sufficiently related to the critical contracts</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>enhanced position management controls and reporting requirements apply, and </core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>new exemptions apply for liquidity providers and for financial firms dealing with non-financial firms that are hedging risks arising from their commercial activities</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For information, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1511764" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Position limits</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1511765" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Position management controls</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1511766" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Position reporting</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1511767" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework—Reform of the UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>EU MAR and UK MAR</core:title><core:para>Certain energy derivatives in the form of ETDs and other financial instruments, if their price or value depends or has an effect on the price or value of any such ETDs, are within the scope of the Market Abuse Regulation (EU) 596/2014 (EU MAR) and Assimilated Regulation (EU) 596/2014 (UK MAR) which applies in the UK. EU MAR and UK MAR prohibit market abuse and specifically insider dealing, unlawful disclosure of inside information and market manipulation.</core:para><core:para>For detailed information on EU MAR and UK MAR, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:6D086E40-8FDE-4D00-84C6-39FBCC522AE9"><lnci:content>EU Market Abuse Regulation (EU MAR)—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:DE029A5A-CFE3-45F5-90EC-1B77F7B7E9D6"><lnci:content>UK Market Abuse Regulation (MAR)—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>EU REMIT and UK REMIT</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 1227/2011</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 1227/2011</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note>Regulation (EU) 1227/2011 (EU REMIT) and Assimilated Regulation (EU) 1227/2011 (UK REMIT), which applies in the UK, contain further prohibitions on market abuse by energy market participants.</core:para><core:para>For more information on EU REMIT and UK REMIT, see Practice Notes: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:683DFAC8-8FE0-4CE2-BE07-7E3A227E5C0C"><lnci:content>An introduction to EU REMIT</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:1C9B3AE9-667F-4824-8EBC-65975EA63CC9"><lnci:content>An introduction to GB REMIT</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164612">Exchange traded energy derivatives</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.ice.com/about/exchanges-clearing">ICE</core:url></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.cmegroup.com/company/nymex.html">NYMEX</core:url></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.cmegroup.com/trading/energy/">CME</core:url></fn:margin-note>Energy derivative contracts in the form of ETDs are also widely traded on stock exchanges such as the ICE Futures market, the Intercontinental Exchange (ICE) or NYMEX. Common products include futures and options contracts on underlying energy commodities such as Brent crude oil, gas and electricity.</core:para></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_164613">Over-the-counter derivatives documentation</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.isda.org/books/" type="https">ISDA Bookstore</core:url></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.isda.org/book/isda-u-s-crude-oil-and-refined-petroleum-products-annex-and-confirmation/" type="https">ISDA US Crude oil and Petroleum Products Annex</core:url></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.isda.org/books/" type="https">ISDA Commodity Annexes</core:url></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.globalcoal.com/scota/aboutscota.cfm" type="http">SCoTA</core:url></fn:margin-note>The documentation of OTC financial derivatives on energy products is frequently negotiated under the ISDA Master Agreement, incorporating by reference the <core:url address="www.isda.org/publications/isdacommderivdefsup.aspx">2005 ISDA Commodity Definitions</core:url> in the confirmation (available for a fee on the ISDA Bookstore). These definitions cover products such as crude oil, natural gas, coal and electricity. In October 2020, ISDA published model clauses to be used with the 2005 ISDA Commodity Definitions. They are designed to enable parties to incorporate express contractual provisions clarifying the consequences of a Floating Amount determined under Section 6.1 (Calculation of a Floating Amount) of the Commodity Definitions being a negative amount. ISDA also produce additional documentation to the Master Agreement such as the US Crude Oil and Refined Petroleum Products Annex and Confirmation, a Supplemental Agreement for Certain Natural Gas Products, or the Physical Coal Annex. The Standard Coal Trading Agreement (SCoTA) is also used in international coal trading.</core:para></tr:secmain></kh:body><kh:related-content type="related-documents"><!--Overview--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:FC4BEB19-8912-47B0-957C-1CA250B6803F"><lnci:content>Sector specific derivatives—overview</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Practice Notes--><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:476F1E1F-D486-46DA-8295-2B1FDD4A4B94"><lnci:content>Banking &amp; Finance glossary</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:8690A9D3-635D-40A5-81B5-1A23D4C4CA7B"><lnci:content>Types of derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:5823ECB8-613E-430A-B0D4-EEFB16DEF701"><lnci:content>Commodity derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:E4EC16C3-6131-4CA9-87B2-22B8C6156DCD"><lnci:content>Market Abuse Regulation (MAR)—essentials [Archived]</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D9D81A5C-9C9B-41CC-900B-A1B3C0AE61F9"><lnci:content>MiFID II &amp; MiFIR—pre- and post-trade transparency</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3E00C247-2B7E-467C-A682-EBA4ECCC0146"><lnci:content>EU MiFID II—commodity derivatives—position limits</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:BF252AB6-49BE-4D79-99B1-283C1F397F30"><lnci:content>UK Market Abuse Regulation (UK MAR)—one minute guide</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:683DFAC8-8FE0-4CE2-BE07-7E3A227E5C0C"><lnci:content>An introduction to EU REMIT</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:DE029A5A-CFE3-45F5-90EC-1B77F7B7E9D6"><lnci:content>UK Market Abuse Regulation (MAR)—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:DB715D8E-82C6-4F8B-9C7C-344CBA3F96B0"><lnci:content>MiFID and non-MiFID business</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:3437B99D-2601-4296-8435-1B7DB33F8B9F"><lnci:content>UK’s commodity derivatives regulatory framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:CFA46F96-3521-45E3-AAB2-0E8A06236592"><lnci:content>UK EMIR—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><!--News Analysis--><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:7D6A4FD1-A3DB-448B-971D-33BCD06665C4"><lnci:content>ESMA guidelines on inside information relating to commodity derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><!--Legislation--><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 600/2014</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 600/2014</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive 2014/65/EU</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Directive (EU) 2021/338</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 596/2014</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 596/2014</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Regulation (EU) 1227/2011</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 1227/2011</lnci:content></lnci:cite><?Pub _newline?><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Regulated Activities) Order 2001, SI 2001/544</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="further-reading"><kh:references ref-type="further-reading"><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The UK's announcement of plans for synthetic LIBOR: panacea or pandora's box? (2020) 8 JIBFL 517</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Insider dealing and commodity derivatives (2016) 6 JIBFL 333</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Energy derivatives and EMIR: is clearing unclear? (2014) 1 JIBFL 60</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Developing carbon structured products (2008) 1 JIBFL 16</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The financial regulation of energy and environmental markets (2011) JFRC 19(4), 355–369</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>UK energy trading regulation: The EMP regime (2002) JFRC 10(2), 168–176</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Close-out Netting and VAT, Supply and Consideration: De Voil Indirect Tax Intelligence, 159 (31)</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para></kh:references></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="external-links"><?Pub _newline?><core:url address="www.isda.org/2021/08/04/isda-response-to-esma-on-technical-standards-for-commodity-derivatives/" type="https">ISDA and FIA response to ESMA consultation on Technical Standards for Commodity Derivatives</core:url><?Pub _newline?><core:url address="www.esma.europa.eu/sites/default/files/library/2015/11/2014-549_-_consultation_paper_mifid_ii_-_mifir.pdf" type="https">ESMA Consultation Paper: MiFID II/MiFIR dated 22 May 2014</core:url><?Pub _newline?><core:url address="www.isda.org/2021/08/04/isda-response-to-esma-on-technical-standards-for-commodity-derivatives/" type="https">ISDA and FIA response to ESMA consultation on Technical Standards for Commodity Derivatives</core:url><?Pub _newline?></kh:related-content></kh:document>