<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "\\voyager\templates\DTDs\LNUK\KnowHow\KnowHow.dtd"><?Pub EntList mdash reg #8364 #176 #169 #8230 #10003 #x2610 #x2611 #x2612 #x2613?><kh:document xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core" xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn" xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/header" xmlns:kh="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/kh" xmlns:lnb="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/lnb" xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci" xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr" xmlns:atict="http://www.arbortext.com/namespace/atict"><atict:info tracking="on" ref="0" print="" color="" /><atict:user user="jimened2" fullname="Jimenez, Steven (REPH-ILO)" color="#D06000" /><atict:user user="jahodovs" fullname="" color="#8000FF" /><kh:body><kh:document-title>The key forms of ISDA credit support documents</kh:document-title><?Pub Caret -3?><kh:mini-summary>This Practice Note describes what the key forms of ISDA credit support documents are and the key differences between the English law credit support annex, English law credit support deed and New York law credit support annex.</kh:mini-summary><!--AI: 27/03/25 SJ using Copilot, UK, Prompt = create two separate tables using the below information (information extracted from subsection 'Which credit support documents relate to initial and variation margin?')--><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_1603912">What does this Practice Note cover?</core:title><core:para>This Practice Note describes:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>what the key forms of ISDA credit support documents are, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the key differences between the English law credit support annex, English law credit support deed and New York law credit support annex</core:para></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_264471">What are the key forms of ISDA credit support document?</core:title><core:para>Credit support is a means of providing collateral or a security interest for payment obligations under derivative transactions (see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:56DF4FF6-5AF2-4BA9-80D8-F926D52A765E"><lnci:content>What is credit support and how is it used in the ISDA credit support documentation</lnci:content></lnci:cite>). The International Swaps and Derivatives Association, Inc (ISDA) has produced standard form credit support documentation which either takes the form of:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>a credit support annex—known as a CSA, or</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>a credit support deed—known as a CSD</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>The key forms of credit support documents published by ISDA are:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Transfer—English law)—known as the English law CSA or the English law annex (the English law Anne—for more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D5A2D4DC-FFF8-4AC8-B4EC-9AB6C7727789"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Transfer—English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>2013 ISDA Standard Credit Support Annex (Transfer—English law) (the English law SCSA)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>ISDA 2016 Credit Support Annex for Variation Margin (VM) (Title Transfer—English Law) (the 2016 CSA VM)—for more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:86B00F85-ADA9-4B3D-B4D2-AEE893BB4DBE"><lnci:content>ISDA 2016 Credit Support Annex for Variation Margin (VM)—clause by clause guide</lnci:content></lnci:cite></core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>1995 ISDA Credit Support Deed (Security Interest—English law)—known as the English law CSD or the English law deed (the English law Deed—for more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:EF97699C-C23F-452C-8930-65AA10AA3FB5"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Deed: Security Interest—English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>ISDA 2016 Phase One Initial Margin (IM) Credit Support Deed (Security Interest—English Law)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>1994 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Security Interest—New York law)—known as the New York law CSA or the New York law annex (the New York law Annex—for more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:AAB6EF40-B788-4EEE-93E3-8277058BD5B1"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Security Interest—New York law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>ISDA 2016 Phase One Credit Support Annex for IM (Security Interest—New York Law)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>ISDA 2016 Credit Support Annex for Variation Margin (VM) (Security Interest—New York Law) </core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>2013 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Security Interest—New York law) (the New York law SCSA)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>2018 ISDA Credit Support Annex for Initial Margin (IM) (Security Interest—New York Law)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>2018 Credit Support Deed for Initial Margin (IM) (Security Interest—English Law)</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>2019 Bank Custodian Collateral Transfer Agreement for Initial Margin and forms of Security Agreement</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>There are also additional credit support documents published by ISDA including the 1995 Credit Support Annex (Japanese law), ISDA 2016 Credit Support Annex for Variation Margin (VM) (Loan—Japanese Law) and ISDA/IIFM 2017 Credit Support Deed for Cash Collateral (VM) but these are not considered in this Practice Note.</core:para><core:para>ISDA also published the 1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Title Transfer—Irish Law) and 1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Title Transfer—French Law) in connection with the new Irish and French law governed 2002 ISDA Master Agreements respectively, which were published in 2018 as part of an ISDA initiative in response to member demand for documentation governed by the laws of an EU Member State in light of Brexit.</core:para></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_264472">Which is the correct ISDA credit support document to use?</core:title><core:para>The English law Annex, English law SCSA and the English law Deed are intended for use with an ISDA Master Agreement that selects English law as its governing law. The New York law Annex and New York law SCSA are intended for use with an ISDA Master Agreement that selects New York law as its governing law. It is usual, although not mandatory, to select a credit support document with a governing law that matches the governing law of the relevant master agreement.</core:para><core:para>It is possible to use a New York law Annex with an English law governed master agreement because although the New York law Annex is an annex to the schedule to an ISDA Master Agreement that selects New York law, it functions as an independent security document. Some adjustments to the wording of the New York law Annex are however required and specific legal advice should be taken on this point.</core:para><core:para>It is highly inadvisable to combine an English law Annex with a New York law governed ISDA master agreement without taking specific legal advice and significantly redrafting the English law Annex. The English law Annex functions as an annex to the schedule to an ISDA master agreement that selects English law as its governing law. It feeds in to the close-out netting provisions in the ISDA master agreement. The consequences of tampering with this mechanism, without careful consideration or legal advice, could be severe.</core:para><core:para>The English law SCSA and New York law SCSA are standardised versions of the English law Annex and New York law Annex. They remove the optionality found in the English law Annex and New York law Annex, encourage the adoption of overnight index swap discounting and create a homogenous valuation framework. However, they otherwise reflect the general features and principles found in the English law Annex and New York law Annex.</core:para><core:para>The credit support documents are all available on the <core:url address="www.isda.org/books" type="https">ISDA Books</core:url> website or the ISDA <core:url address="www.isda.org/isda-solutions-infohub/mylibrary/" type="https">MyLibrary</core:url> platform, for a fee.</core:para></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_264473">ISDA credit support documents—a quick compare and contrast</core:title><tr:secsub1><core:title>Features that are common to the English law Annex, 2016 CSA VM, English law Deed and New York law Annex</core:title><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>credit support is provided by one counterparty delivering assets to the other</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>they all secure the net exposure of one counterparty to the other under a specific master agreement</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the arrangements are bilateral—each counterparty could be a provider of collateral at one point in time and a receiver of collateral at another point in time, depending on the net exposure between the counterparties, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>the collateral required under the credit support is periodically adjusted on a <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_1528694" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:476F1E1F-D486-46DA-8295-2B1FDD4A4B94"><lnci:content>mark-to-market</lnci:content></lnci:cite> basis</core:para></core:listitem></core:list></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Transfer—English law), 2013 ISDA Standard Credit Support Annex (Transfer—English law) and 2016 CSA VM</core:title><core:para>The English law Annex, the English law SCSA and the 2016 CSA VM:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>do not create a security interest—they constitute an outright transfer of title to collateral</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>form part of the schedule to the master agreement, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>constitute a transaction (as defined in the ISDA Master Agreement)</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D5A2D4DC-FFF8-4AC8-B4EC-9AB6C7727789"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Transfer—English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>1995 ISDA Credit Support Deed (Security Interest—English law)</core:title><core:para>The English law Deed:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>creates a security interest in the collateral</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>does not form part of the schedule to the master agreement—it is a standalone agreement, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>constitutes a credit support document (as defined in the ISDA Master Agreement)</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:EF97699C-C23F-452C-8930-65AA10AA3FB5"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Deed: Security Interest—English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1><tr:secsub1><core:title>1994 ISDA Credit Support Annex (Security Interest—New York law) and 2013 ISDA Standard Credit Support Annex (Security Interest—New York law)</core:title><core:para>The New York law Annex and New York law SCSA:</core:para><core:list type="bullet"><core:listitem><core:para>grants a security interest in the collateral</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>forms part of the schedule to the master agreement, and</core:para></core:listitem><core:listitem><core:para>constitutes a credit support document (as defined in the ISDA Master Agreement)</core:para></core:listitem></core:list><core:para>For more information, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:AAB6EF40-B788-4EEE-93E3-8277058BD5B1"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Security Interest—New York law</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secsub1></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_386028">Which credit support documents relate to initial and variation margin?</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite></fn:margin-note><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.cftc.gov/sites/default/files/idc/groups/public/@swaps/documents/file/hr4173_enrolledbill.pdf">The Dodd Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act 2010</core:url></fn:margin-note>In 2016, ISDA introduced a new suite of credit support documents which are designed to facilitate compliance with margin requirements for derivatives that are not subject to mandatory clearing under the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EU) 648/2012 (OJ L 201, 27.7.2012, p. 1) (EU EMIR) in the EU, Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012 (UK EMIR) in the UK and the <core:url address="www.cftc.gov/idc/groups/public/@swaps/documents/file/hr4173_enrolledbill.pdf">Dodd Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act</core:url> (the Dodd Frank Act) in the US.</core:para><core:para>The 2016 Phase One credit support documents for IM allow parties subject to regulatory margin requirements on 1 September 2016 (Phase One Entities) to establish IM arrangements that meet the requirements on margin for uncleared swaps. The documents are designed specifically for use between Phase One Entities and act in the same way as the corresponding 'standard' credit support document eg the 2016 Phase One Credit Support Annex governed by New York law also grants a security interest, forms part of the schedule to the master agreement and constitutes a credit support document, just as the 1994 ISDA Credit Support Annex governed by New York law does. </core:para><core:para>The 2018 credit support documents for IM (comprising the 2018 ISDA Credit Support Annex for Initial Margin (IM) (Security Interest—New York Law) and 2018 Credit Support Deed for Initial Margin (IM) (Security Interest—English Law) are adapted from the 2016 forms for use by buy- and sell-side firms in view of the expansion of the impact of IM regulations to firms coming into scope since September 2019 (Phase 4 onwards).The 2019 Bank Custodian Collateral Transfer Agreement for Initial Margin and forms of Security Agreement are used to document a collateral arrangement between two parties where the collateral is held in a bank custodian account for use in complying with initial margin requirements.</core:para><core:para>The credit support documents relating to variation margin are updated versions of the corresponding credit support document (eg the 1994 ISDA Credit Support Annex governed by New York law and 1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex governed by English law). However, the documents are limited to variation margin. Through these credit support documents, parties can establish variation margin arrangements that meet the requirements of new regulations on margin for uncleared swaps.</core:para><core:para>In July 2019, ISDA published <core:url address="www.isda.org/book/isda-template-collateral-schedules/">template collateral schedules</core:url> which provide counterparties with pre-selected lists of collateral types and minimum regulatory haircuts. These are designed to be used as a starting point for negotiation between parties in scope for regulatory IM.</core:para><core:para>On 8 December 2021, ISDA published <core:url address="www.isda.org/book/isda-supplemental-regime-definitions-for-use-with-regulatory-margin-collateral-documentation/" type="https">supplemental definitions</core:url> for use with ISDA’s regulatory margin documentation, to assist market participants in incorporating descriptions of applicable regulatory regimes into their regulatory IM bilateral agreements, as new regimes have come into force since the publication of those credit support documents.</core:para><core:para>For more information on the credit support documents for IM and VM, see news analysis: <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:88059B6F-01C9-4904-A326-34649B0FA3F7"><lnci:content>Uncleared derivatives—IM and VM credit support documentation</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para><!--AI: 27/03/25--><core:para>The following table summarises the ISDA credit support documents for IM:</core:para><table><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col2" /><colspec colname="col3" /><thead><row><entry valign="top"><core:para>Document Name</core:para></entry><entry valign="top"><core:para>Description</core:para></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry><core:para>2016 ISDA Credit Support Annex for Initial Margin (Security Interest—New York Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Designed for Phase One Entities to establish IM arrangements that meet regulatory requirements for uncleared swaps.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2016 ISDA Credit Support Deed for Initial Margin (Security Interest—English Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Similar to the New York law version but governed by English law.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2018 ISDA Credit Support Annex for Initial Margin (Security Interest—New York Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Adapted from the 2016 forms for use by buy- and sell-side firms coming into scope since September 2019 (Phase 4 onwards).</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2018 ISDA Credit Support Deed for Initial Margin (Security Interest—English Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Similar to the New York law version but governed by English law.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2019 Bank Custodian Collateral Transfer Agreement for Initial Margin</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Used to document collateral arrangements where collateral is held in a bank custodian account.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2019 Forms of Security Agreement</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Used in conjunction with the Bank Custodian Collateral Transfer Agreement for Initial Margin.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2019 Template Collateral Schedules</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Provide counterparties with pre-selected lists of collateral types and minimum regulatory haircuts, designed as a starting point for negotiation between parties in scope for regulatory IM.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2021 Supplemental Definitions</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Assist market participants in incorporating descriptions of applicable regulatory regimes into their regulatory IM bilateral agreements, as new regimes have come into force since the publication of those documents.</core:para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><core:para>The following table summarises the ISDA credit support documents for VM:</core:para><table><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><thead><row><entry valign="top"><core:para>Document Name</core:para></entry><entry valign="top"><core:para>Description</core:para></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry><core:para>1994 ISDA Credit Support Annex (New York Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Updated for variation margin requirements.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>1995 ISDA Credit Support Annex (English Law)</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Updated for variation margin requirements.</core:para></entry></row><row><entry><core:para>2016 ISDA Variation Margin Protocol</core:para></entry><entry><core:para>Helps market participants comply with new rules on margin for uncleared swaps by providing a scalable solution to amend derivatives contract documentation with multiple counterparties.</core:para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><!--AI End--><core:para>For more information on margin for uncleared swaps generally, see Practice Note: <lnci:cite citeref="CITEID_731296" normcite="urn:editpractgpn:CFA46F96-3521-45E3-AAB2-0E8A06236592"><lnci:content>UK EMIR—essentials—Margin requirements</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and Articles: <lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Saying how versus saying what: the choice of regulatory style in margin policy (2022) 5 JIBFL 335</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Challenges ahead of the initial margin “big bang” (2019) 7 JIBFL 453</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>How soon is now? Release of collateral in initial margin arrangements (2019) 7 JIBFL 431</lnci:content></lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The future: margining uncleared derivatives (2013) 11 JIBFL 705</lnci:content></lnci:cite> and <lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Margin for error (2016) 6 JIBFL 351</lnci:content></lnci:cite>.</core:para></tr:secmain><tr:secmain><core:title id="CITEID_386029">ISDA Regulatory Initial Margin AANA Self-Disclosure Letter</core:title><core:para><fn:margin-note><core:url address="www.isda.org/book/isda-regulatory-initial-margin-aana-self-disclosure-letter-june-18-2021/">ISDA Regulatory Initial Margin AANA Self-Disclosure Letter (18 June 2021)</core:url></fn:margin-note>In June 2021, ISDA published the ISDA Regulatory Initial Margin AANA Self-Disclosure Letter and accompanying Answer Sheet which is intended to provide a standard form for market participants to communicate certain information needed to determine which trading relationships are, or may become, subject to regulatory IM requirements, and how IM calculations will need to be performed. It allows entities to disclose information identifying whether it is a member of a group and which AANA thresholds (by regime) the entity (or its group) has exceeded for the relevant year. From this information, parties can determine how much IM needs to be paid to comply with IM obligations.</core:para></tr:secmain></kh:body><kh:related-content type="further-reading"><kh:references ref-type="further-reading"><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The initial margin “big bang”: the aftermath (2023) 7 JIBFL 488</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Saying how versus saying what: the choice of regulatory style in margin policy (2022) 5 JIBFL 335</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Challenges ahead of the initial margin “big bang” (2019) 7 JIBFL 453</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>How soon is now? Release of collateral in initial margin arrangements (2019) 7 JIBFL 431</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Margin for error (2016) 6 JIBFL 351</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The future: margining uncleared derivatives (2013) 11 JIBFL 705</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, 9.18" type="comm"><lnci:content>Credit Support Legal Risk and Documentation: Henderson on Derivatives [9.18]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="HD, 9.18" type="comm"><lnci:content>Credit Support Legal Risk and Documentation: Henderson on Derivatives [9.18]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The rising risks and roles of financial collateral (2014) 1 JIBFL 3</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>The future: margining uncleared derivatives (2013) 11 JIBFL 705</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite type="journal"><lnci:content>Collateral and OTC derivatives after the credit crunch (2009) 5 JIBFL 262</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="LPTS, 25.01" type="comm"><lnci:content>1995 ISDA credit support annex (bilateral form—transfer): The Law and Practice of True Sale, para 25.01</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="COLMPODT, 2.2" type="comm"><lnci:content>Credit Support Providers and Credit Support Documents: Close-outs: The Law and Market Practice of OTC Derivative Terminations [2.2]–[2.12]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="COLMPODT, 4.50" type="comm"><lnci:content>The effect of early termination on ISDA Credit Support Documents: Close-outs: The Law and Market Practice of OTC Derivative Terminations [4.50]–[4.71]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para><kh:reference-para><lnci:cite normcite="COLMPODT, 8.19" type="comm"><lnci:content>The importance of collateral arrangements: Close-outs: The Law and Market Practice of OTC Derivative Terminations [8.19]–[8.23]</lnci:content></lnci:cite></kh:reference-para></kh:references></kh:related-content><kh:related-content type="related-documents"><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:5685F518-BB89-4AFF-9176-07500B4EC4A7"><lnci:content>Collateral and credit support—overview</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:D5A2D4DC-FFF8-4AC8-B4EC-9AB6C7727789"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Transfer—English law</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:AAB6EF40-B788-4EEE-93E3-8277058BD5B1"><lnci:content>ISDA Credit Support Annex: Security Interest—New York law</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:86B00F85-ADA9-4B3D-B4D2-AEE893BB4DBE"><lnci:content>ISDA 2016 Credit Support Annex for Variation Margin (VM)—clause by clause guide</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:C9DA7671-21A2-4B40-A2E5-ACFA748E4AF5"><lnci:content>Derivatives: ISDA documentation framework</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:56DF4FF6-5AF2-4BA9-80D8-F926D52A765E"><lnci:content>What is credit support and how is it used in the ISDA credit support documentation</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:CFA46F96-3521-45E3-AAB2-0E8A06236592"><lnci:content>UK EMIR—essentials</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:369597D0-6F6C-4FBC-B2E6-AC61E78282D8"><lnci:content>ISDA Variation Margin Protocol—what is it about?</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:DD35C9E1-43D3-4E03-9E9C-CA9792653950"><lnci:content>New margining requirements for uncleared derivatives</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:88059B6F-01C9-4904-A326-34649B0FA3F7"><lnci:content>Uncleared derivatives—IM and VM credit support documentation</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite><lnci:content>European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite><lnci:cite><lnci:content>Assimilated Regulation (EU) 648/2012</lnci:content></lnci:cite><core:url address="www.isda.org/a/vufgE/Benchmarking-Generative-AI-for-CSA-Clause-Extraction-and-CDM-Representation.pdf" type="https">ISDA: Benchmarking Generative AI for CSA Clause Extraction and CDM Representation</core:url></kh:related-content></kh:document>